A Final Word

Sometimes when I study the Bible, I get hung up on the details. I know I shouldn’t, but I do. Take that incident where Jesus provided supper for about fifteen thousand men, women, and children. All four of the authors who describe Jesus’s ministry mention it. They use the event to show us some lofty insights about their Lord. I am ready to get on to those grand lessons, but then John sidetracks me with the detail that it was some nameless youngster who supplied the five rolls and the two small fish Jesus used to perform the miracle. Frankly, I can’t get past that kid.

It was a miracle of sorts, wasn’t it, that the boy hadn’t already devoured his lunch? After all, it was late in the afternoon, and everyone else was getting hungry. Boys I know are always hungry. When I take my grandsons to a ball game, the first thing they want to do is buy a hot dog and a soda. In fact, they would be content to spend the afternoon at the concession stand eating. Here in John’s Gospel, the day was drifting toward evening, and this youngster hadn’t touched the lunch his mother made for him that morning.

Perhaps he was too excited to eat. Not much happens in a small community. Villagers take their excitement wherever they can find it. In this case, a popular young teacher had come to the area, and he had performed some miracles. He was a happening. Everyone wanted to hear what he would say and to see what he would do. This boy didn’t want to miss out on anything that big. He raced to stay ahead of the crowd, to find the best spot up front, to catch what was going on. He didn’t want to pass half a day looking at some adult’s backside.

Maybe the rush and movement kept him from eating his lunch at noon. I have another question: What made him decide to donate his lunch to Jesus? Okay, Andrew asked him for it. But imagine the conversation: “Look, son, the people are hungry, and we have to find some way to feed them. Is that your lunch? Would you mind letting Jesus have it? We’re trying to scrape up something—anything. Your lunch might help.”

Wouldn’t any normal kid have responded, “Mister, you’re crazy! All I’ve got is five rolls and a couple of sardines. And I’m getting really hungry myself. I haven’t eaten anything since breakfast. This won’t even be enough for me. You’ve been out in the sun too long if you think what I’ve got in this bag could feed this crowd.” That’s what I would have said. Wouldn’t you?

But for some reason, this lad went along with it. He surrendered his lunch to Andrew, who in turn handed it over to Jesus. “Here is a boy with five small barley loaves and two small fish,” he reported, “but how far will they go among so many?”

The answer to that is easy: Not far. Not far at all.

There’s something else. When the disciples fed the crowd, how did they manage to get everyone to eat the same menu? Weren’t there some people in the crowd who complained about the food? Weren’t a number of them picky eaters? Fish, with bread, isn’t everybody’s favorite dish. In a gathering that large, there must have been some who had eaten some spoiled fish when they were growing up and couldn’t stomach it as adults. Did everyone in the crowd realize how hungry they were or how desperately they needed to eat something nourishing that afternoon? I know that the text tells us that everybody had enough, but isn’t it possible that some of the basketfuls left over came from people who refused to eat the entrée?

Don’t you identify with that youngster and with Andrew? Any preacher does. No one in their right mind who thought about it would ever choose to be a preacher. It’s a commitment to the impossible. As I enter the pulpit, I wonder, “How can what I have prepared possibly feed so many?” My best sermons are little more than some fish and chips, and at times they are a bit greasy. Isn’t it folly to believe that what I have in my hand could possibly meet the hunger of an entire congregation?

After you give it your best shot,

when you do the most diligent exegesis you can do,

when you have read the best commentaries and crafted your sermon with skill and then delivered it with passion,

even if you follow all the counsel I have given you in this book,

let’s face it: at best you have two small fish and five rolls. (All right, if you’re really gifted, you may have three fish and an extra roll or two.) But you never have enough to feed the multitude.

Only Jesus Christ through his Spirit can do that. You must give your sermon to him. Preaching is ultimately his work. It’s astonishing how he not only multiplies our efforts but also creates in listeners a hunger for what we offer them.

Every preacher knows the surprise. The woman who calls you in the middle of the week to thank you for your sermon—“particularly that part about apologizing to your children when you have messed up.” You think back through the message, and you hadn’t preached about that at all. Or you celebrated communion and spoke a brief word about the death and resurrection of Jesus. You learn later that a person in your congregation who had begun an affair broke it off because God had spoken to them that morning. You never had someone like that in mind at all. You get a note, unsigned, that simply says, “Thank you for letting God use you. You’ll never know the difference it has made.” You wonder how or why or when. Christ has a secret passageway into people’s lives that you and I know little about. Give your sermon to him.

Of course, we will not give God that which costs us nothing. We will give him our best. Yet in the final analysis, there are no great preachers. There’s only a great Christ who does startling things when we place ourselves and our preaching in his hands.

William Barclay, who himself held onto the faith with shaky hands, told about A. J. Gossip, a man “who lived closer to God than any man I have ever known.” At one time Gossip was minister of St. Matthew’s Church in Glasgow. There was a week when he experienced pressures that every preacher knows, pressures that made it impossible for him to prepare as he should.

“You know the stair up to the pulpit in St. Matthew’s?” Gossip asked. “You know the bend in the stair? Jesus Christ met me there. I saw Him as clearly as I see you. He looked at the sermon in my hand. ‘Gossip,’ He said to me, ‘is this the best you could do for me this week?’” Gossip went on: “Thinking back over the pressures of that week, I could honestly say: ‘Yes, Lord, it is my best.’” Then Gossip said, “Jesus Christ took that poor thing that Sunday morning and in his hands it became a trumpet!”1

It is always so. Even on our best weeks, we have only some fish and bread. But we serve the living Lord. Give him your small lunch and trust him to feed his people.

1 Barclay, Spiritual Autobiography, 13.

Sample Sermon and Evaluation

What follows is a sermon I preached based on Matthew 20:1–16. If you take a look at the passage, you will find that it has its roots in chapter 19, and therefore the chapter division is an unfortunate one. It is offered not as a model sermon but merely as one that has grown out of the process we have just discussed. It would be wise to take a few moments to read the passage so that you have it in mind. Once you read the sermon, we’ll look back at it together. We will use it to review what we have discussed in the previous pages. (The paragraphs are numbered in order to refer back to them in the closing discussion.)

Sermon: “The Great Wage Dispute”

1. Jesus made a wise midcareer adjustment. Until the time he was thirty, he had worked in the firm of “Joseph and Sons Carpenters” in the town of Nazareth. Then God called him to preach. Many observers feel that the switch of professions was a fortunate one. If he had stayed in business, he would have gone bankrupt.

2. At least that’s what many hardheaded business types might feel when they read this account of a labor dispute that Jesus told with obvious approval in Matthew 20:1–16. As a case study on how to handle labor management relations, it gives a business analyst cold chills.

3. The story starts out sensibly enough. It’s harvest season, and early in the morning, a grape grower drives into the center of town. He goes to the corner where farmworkers assemble hoping for a day’s work, and the grower selects some of these men to pick grapes for him. Before they go out to the vineyard, he signs a contract with them to pay a denarius for the day’s work. At the time a glut existed in the labor force, and a denarius was a generous wage. The owner didn’t have to pay that much, but you can overlook his lack of haggling because the man wasn’t very astute about business affairs.

4. Then later, at nine o’clock in the morning, the owner returned to town and saw some other men standing around waiting for someone to hire them. The owner sent this group, too, into his vineyard, but this time without a contract. He promised only to “do what is right.” That would unsettle any union leader. A loose arrangement is no substitute for a contract. But face it, you have to put up with agreements like that when work is hard to find.

5. At noon and then again at three o’clock, the vineyard owner returned, and when he spotted other unemployed workers, he sent them into his vineyard to pick the grapes. It’s the same deal as before. No contract. Just his assurance that he will do what is right by them.

6. Finally, at five in the afternoon, as the owner was about to call it a day, he saw some other workers standing on the corner with their tools. He stopped and asked them why they weren’t working. “We’ve been standing here all day waiting for someone to hire us,” they explained. So with only an hour left before sundown, he sent those workers to pick grapes in his vineyard. I suppose the workers were grateful. After all, any work is better than nothing. Even a small paycheck would put some food on their tables.

7. The problem started an hour later, at six, when the closing whistle blew. The vineyard owner ordered his foreman to pay the workers. The owner was obviously more eccentric than efficient. He got everything backward. He insisted that the last fellows hired be paid first and the first hired be paid last. So when the laborers lined up last man first, the foreman paid the crew that had worked only sixty minutes a denarius, a full day’s wage. The workers who punched in at three and those who signed on at noon also got paid a denarius. In fact, that was true for those who had worked since nine that morning. Those at the back of the line who had started at sunrise got their expectations up. “Hey, there’s a bonus today!”

8. But no. When they finally shuffled up to the pay window and received their pay envelope, it contained the denarius they had agreed on. Tempers flared, and they sent their representative to the owner to have it out with him. “Look,” he argued, “these last guys you hired worked only an hour, and you made them equal to us. It’s not right. We picked those lousy grapes all day in the sweltering heat. It’s tough work, and our hands and backs are sore. We want to file a grievance. We deserve better. You’re guilty of unfair labor practices.”

9. I don’t know how this incident sits with you, but I suspect you want to grab a picket sign and join the workers’ protest. This upside-down system of payment strikes us as grossly unfair—just as it did to the workers and to the audience that first heard the story. (What’s going on? Why did Jesus tell this story? What’s he driving at?)

10. Well, Jesus certainly didn’t offer this parable as a model for how Christians should settle wage disputes in the twenty-first century. Imagine the ruckus the press would set up if an employer tried this today. He couldn’t operate. He couldn’t get to his office because of the picket lines he would have to cross. If he did pay his workers this way one week, he would learn his lesson the following week. His labor force would be crushed in the five o’clock rush going to work. Production would collapse. With workers putting in only an hour a day, the work would never get done. (We had better understand why Jesus told this story. Is he completely unaware of how business works? Why did he tell a story as crazy as this?)

11. The context gives us a clue to what Jesus is driving at. The parable follows Jesus’s response to two different men who wanted to sign a contract with God. The first chap was a wealthy young man (Matt. 19:16–26). He approached Jesus to ask him to spell out exactly what he had to do to earn eternal life. He figured that he had kept the Ten Commandments, but he wanted to know if Jesus could think of anything else that might be involved to qualify. Jesus knew that this man needed radical surgery, so he put his scalpel on the cancer in the man’s life: “Sell your possessions, and give the money to the poor, and you will have treasure in heaven. Then come and follow me.” If he wanted a contract, he could have it. But the price was more than the young man was willing to pay. He called the whole thing off. His investments and his bank accounts meant everything to him—more than God, or eternal life, or heaven. That’s why this prosperous young man walked away from the deal.

12. The second man who wanted to negotiate a contract was Peter (Matt. 19:25–30). He and the other disciples had overheard the conversation with the wealthy inquirer. As a result Peter raised a candid question. “Look, we have left everything to follow you; what’s in it for us?” Peter’s question sounds self-serving, but some time or other, most of us get around to asking it. At first, when we sign on to follow Jesus, we may not bring up the question. But then, after we have labored in the heat of the day, we get uneasy. Things happen. “What’s the deal?” we ask. “What’s in it for us?”

13. Some time or other, we all get around to Peter’s question. Perhaps you have hit some financial difficulties. You see yourself as a dedicated follower of Jesus. Yet you have to struggle to make ends meet. Others don’t have to struggle with a tight budget. It doesn’t seem fair. What’s the payoff for your commitment? What’s in it for you?

14. Perhaps you wrestle with health problems. You have served Christ with all your strength, but now you no longer have any. Your health and strength are gone. You wonder, “Lord, what’s happening? I’ve tried to do your work. Yet new Christians who haven’t served as long and faithfully as I have are vibrant and healthy. It’s not fair. What’s my reward? What’s in it for me?”

15. Perhaps you have gone to serve Jesus in another part of the world and have struggled with the anxiety and frustration of coping in a different culture. Other Christians stay at home and live in the luxury of affluent America. You take the pressure on yourself and on your family, but every victory is offset by a setback. You have won some and lost some. So what do you get for your sacrifice? You ask, “What’s in it for me?”

16. Or you serve in a church where you feel that people have badly mistreated you and taken advantage of you. You hang on when you want to hang it up. Other Christians seem to thrive in their service. They don’t seem to have labored as hard or as long as you, but they are doing well. The question nags at you, “So what do I get out of it?”

17. (“What’s in it for us?” There’s a bargaining streak in Peter’s question. But you have to identify with him. Peter felt that he had good reason to ask the question: “We’ve given up everything to follow you; what do we get out of it?”)

18. Jesus responded with gentleness and grace to Peter’s question. He could have made Peter feel guilty.

19. Jesus might have said, “Okay, Peter, let’s put it all down where we can look at it. What precisely did you give up? You say you gave up your position as vice president of the Zebedee Fish Company. You gave up a promising career in fishing. That’s impressive. What else?

20. “That’s true, you gave her up too. She was a pretty little thing. She had lovely curves and a beautiful shape. You loved to spend time with her. In fact, you thought you would probably spend your life with her. Yes, we’ll put that down, Peter. You turned your back on your boat to follow me.”

21. If Peter had compiled a list of things that he had given up to follow Christ, Jesus could have shamed him. They seem trivial. Instead, Jesus assured Peter that he and those like him would be well repaid. In the future, when Jesus sets up his kingdom, Peter and his friends would have positions beyond the wildest dreams of any Galilean fisherman. Whatever anyone had given up to follow Jesus will be repaid a hundred times over in addition to receiving eternal life. For Peter and those like him, the best was yet to come. God would never be in their debt.

22. Then Jesus made the statement “But many who are first will be last, and many who are last will be first” (Matt. 19:30). It’s a weird saying. It is so important, though, that Jesus rephrased it again at the end of his story: “So the last will be first, and the first will be last” (20:16). What’s that all about? It sounds like pious nonsense. “The first shall be last, and the last shall be first” doesn’t work if you are standing in line at the checkout counter at the supermarket, or waiting in a long line at the airport, or lining up to be served at the bakery, where everyone takes a number.

23. Actually, it doesn’t work any place that I can think of. In our society the first are first, and the last are last. That’s the way the system works in sports, in government, in education, in business, and in vineyards. In those realms the last are last, and the first are first. But Jesus declares that’s not the way it works in his kingdom. In his setup “many who are first will be last, and many who are last will be first.” (What does it mean? What does it mean in the kingdom to have our order of things reversed? Does it make any sense?)

24. “The first shall be last, and the last first” means that Jesus changes the order of things. The reason for this reversal is that God deals with us not on the basis of our merit but on the basis of his goodness. We live with a merit system. The people who arrive first get served first. The people who work more hours make more money. The students who make the best grades go to the top of the class. God doesn’t work with that system. He rewards us not on the basis of our merit but on the basis of his goodness. He doesn’t give us what we deserve. He gives us more than we deserve. He is always fair, but far better than fair, he is always good.

25. Look at what this story shows us. To be allowed to go to work in his vineyard reflects God’s goodness. Service in itself is an undeserved reward. Those men standing idle in the square before sundown were not “the idle rich.” They were “the idle poor.” Unemployment ran high in the country. Work was hard to find. Their pathetic explanation tells us why they were standing there: “Because no one would hire us.” That means “No one wants us” or “No one needs us.” If you have ever spent days or weeks desperately looking for a job, you know that it’s more exhausting standing in an unemployment line than working on an assembly line.

26. I have a friend in his early fifties who lost his job when his company downsized. For weeks that man scoured the city trying to find another position. He was willing to take almost any job available, but no firm was interested. It almost killed him. In fact, he grew so depressed that he contemplated suicide.

27. If when you get out of bed in the morning you have meaningful work to do, instead of resenting the alarm clock, breathe a prayer of thanks that you have a job to go to. It is terrifying when a society can’t provide employment for someone who wants to work. People seldom crack up under the strain of hard work. They come apart because of meaningless inactivity. The toughest challenge in life is not when you have to work hard. It’s when you don’t have any work to do at all.

28. Jesus comes to the idle, the unemployed, the lost who have time on their hands and offers us meaningful work to do in his vineyard. That work is in itself a gift. There is fulfillment in serving the Lord of the vineyard. In his work we have a relation with him and his harvest. The people to be pitied are not the workers in the vineyard but the idle in the marketplace.

29. Do you doubt that? Compare Peter with that rich young man. Putting aside all the religious jargon for a moment, whose life was better spent? Would you seriously suggest that Peter would have been better off if he could have stayed in the fishing business and become a tycoon? By the standards of their society, the wealthy young man was a “first” and Peter was a “last.” But don’t you feel some sorrow for that young man, who turned away from following Jesus and missed out on the timeless life of God? The person to pity is the man or woman who crawls out of bed in the morning, grabs a cup of coffee at the local Starbucks, fights the traffic to the same office, eats at the same restaurant, leaves the same tip, drives home at the same time, watches television, and then falls into bed. He or she retires at sixty-five, plays golf until seventy-three, and dies with no sense of the eternal about life. Who ends up being first? Who ends up being last?

30. By sending us into the vineyard to work, Jesus delivers us from eternal insignificance. When the Tartar tribes of Central Asia curse their enemies, they don’t tell them to “go to hell.” Instead, they say, “May you do nothing forever.” Jesus Christ in his goodness delivers us from that curse. (There is reward just to work in the vineyard, and when it comes to the payoff itself, we can count on God’s generous goodness to determine our reward.)

31. This parable assures us that our Master is much more than just. He is always that, but he is much more than that. He is generous and good. Listen again to the interaction that the owner of the vineyard had with his disgruntled workers (Matt. 19:12–15). They protest that he is unfair. After all, they argue, they had to sweat for twelve hours while some of the other grape pickers had to work for only one. The owner defends himself: “Look, I was not unjust to you. You received everything we agreed on. Certainly, you can’t argue that I don’t have full rights over my possessions, can you? I am free to give to the others as much as I gave you.” The owner gave unequal treatment, but it was not unjust treatment. He had not wronged the first workers to favor their friends. Those early workers received everything they had agreed on. Everything.

32. The vineyard owner, in paying off his workers, gave everyone justice. With most of the workers, however, he went beyond what was just. He acted out of the goodness of his heart. Justice forms the background of this story, against which goodness appears as goodness and not unfairness. The owner would have been evil if he had cheated those early workers out of what they had bargained for. The emphasis of the parable falls on his magnificent generosity to those eleventh-hour workers. Everyone in the story was treated fairly, but the last men in were also treated with lavish generosity.

33. When you serve Jesus Christ, you don’t work for a wage; you receive a reward. In his service you are rewarded based not on your merit alone but on his generosity. You are not rewarded for the quality of your work—you pick delicious grapes. You are not rewarded for the quantity of your work—you pick more grapes in an hour than the others do in twelve. When you serve Jesus Christ, he does not put you under contract. He puts you under grace.

34. That’s how you become a Christian. Salvation is based entirely on God’s grace and not on your merit. If you think that you come into a relationship with God based on what you do, you are doomed never to have eternal life at all. That’s why the rich man missed it. He couldn’t understand that Christ turns our system upside down. He wanted a contract based on his merit, but when he got one, he couldn’t handle it. He couldn’t get it out of his head that God doesn’t work in a system where the first are first and the last are last.

35. Peter was inclined to think that after following Jesus everything changed back to the old bookkeeping system. Shouldn’t the first, who have given up the most, have preference over the last? Peter wanted to go back to a wage system. But wages are the wrong way to think about God’s dealing with us. The focus of this story is not on how to earn a salary but on the generous reward of God. It is wrongheaded to bargain with God. We ought to enter into his service with gratitude that we have meaningful work to do and leave the ultimate reward with him. Jesus wants to treat both the first and the last as objects of his generous goodness.

36. (How do you react to the goodness of God?) Most of us are delighted—even thankful—when we sense his bounty in our lives. I suppose those men who worked for an hour and received a full day’s pay cheered the owner for his goodness. The test, however, is not how you respond to the goodness of God when it is showered on you but how you react when you see it displayed to others.

37. The owner asks, “Are you envious because I am good? Do you begrudge me my generosity to others?” In other words he asks, “Are you uptight because I have shown these other workers a measure of generosity they have not deserved? I haven’t given you less than you had coming to you, have I? You don’t suffer at all because I was openhanded in rewarding these other workers, do you? Are you begrudging me my right to give these other fellows more than they have earned?”

38. We respond, “Of course not, Lord. We’re delighted that you are generous to our friends—that’s very nice.” Yet all the time, we are thinking, “Why not me? Why should my friends get to stand around all day when I have to sweat through the heat of the afternoon? Why do other Christians have it easier than I do? When do I get paid?”

39. Isn’t it usually when I see God do something out of the ordinary for a close friend or a colleague that I get upset with the way God has dealt with me? It’s then that I may ignore completely God’s goodness in my life, and in my heart, I accuse God of being terribly unfair. When I have a contract mentality, that’s where I end up.

40. (What is the solution to this attitude? How do I keep from grumbling against the generosity of God? How do I keep from getting upset when God, in his goodness, allows the last to be first and the first to be last?)

41. The laborers were satisfied as long as they dealt with the owner alone. As long as they focused on the denarius and the work they were given, they were content. It was not until the others showed up and received their pay that the haggling broke out. Then envy set in. Isn’t it true that our angry feelings about God’s goodness start when we look at the other workers in the vineyard and decide what God should or should not do in their lives compared to what God has done for us?

42. As long as you concentrate on working for the owner of the vineyard, gathering his crop, nothing else matters very much. If you understand that he has given you productive work to do and always rewards you out of his generous goodness, you will be satisfied. Realize your Lord doesn’t work in the marketplace system, based on “the first will be first, and the last last.” His goodness turns that system downside up. “The first shall be last, and the last shall be first.” Meister Eckhart, the mystic, understood this when he wrote, “The foundation of spiritual blessing is this—the soul looks to the goodness of God with nothing in between.”

43. Years ago, when our son Torrey was ten or eleven, he came home early one Saturday afternoon from playing with his friends. His mother was frantically trying to get things ready for company that evening. Without being asked Torrey got out the vacuum cleaner and vacuumed the whole house. Bonnie told me about it when I got home. I usually paid the kids fifty cents for a job like that. When I asked Torrey what I owed him, he replied, “Dad, I just wanted to help.” I pulled out my wallet and gave him two dollars. He took it and said, “Dad, I like being in this family. You gave me more than I would have asked for and more than the job was worth!” He honored me more than he knew. Over thirty years have passed since that incident, but I’ve never forgotten it. How satisfying to have a son who loves you and pitches in and doesn’t take your generosity for granted.

Evaluation

Now let’s look at the sermon with a series of questions and answers.

What Are the Subject, the Complement, and the Exegetical Idea of the Passage?

Subject: Why is the system of payment reversed in the kingdom of heaven?

Complement: Because God deals with people not on the basis of merit but on the basis of his goodness and generosity.

Idea: In the kingdom of heaven, God reverses the human system of wages because he deals with people not on the basis of merit but on the basis of his goodness and generosity.

Exegetical observation: The parable elaborates on the enigmatic saying in Matthew 19:30, “But many who are first shall be last, and the last shall be first.” Notice the for that opens chapter 20 and tells us that the parable elaborates on that statement. It is the idea of the parable.

What Is the Homiletical Idea of the Sermon?

I played with several statements that I might use:

“God works on an upside-down system of rewards.”

“Don’t work for God’s favor; accept it.”

“Work for God, not a wage.”

None of these stirred my imagination. I decided, therefore, to go with Jesus’s statement, “The first shall be last, and the last shall be first.” People may have heard that statement because it’s occasionally used in common speech, but most would have no idea where it comes from or what it means. I decided that if I explained the saying, then when listeners heard it again it, they would bring the theological truth to mind.

What Is the Purpose of Preaching This Sermon?

My purpose was to have listeners respond positively to God’s goodness in their own lives and respond to it positively when they witnessed God’s goodness in the lives of others.

What Is the Need for This Sermon?

Many Christians feel that God isn’t fair. Usually, that comes from comparing how God has dealt with them to how God has dealt with others. That leads to envy, which rots the soul. Just as the Pharisees were upset when Jesus welcomed sinners, Christians can be upset when God’s goodness is shown to others. We can feel that we alone should be the special objects of his generosity.

Does the Sermon Have an Outline?

Yes, the outline looked like this:

1. Introduction: It raises the question, “What’s going on in this parable?” (paragraphs 1–10)

2. We’re tempted to get into a contract relationship with God. (paragraphs 11–23)

Jesus didn’t offer this parable as a model for settling wage disputes in the twenty-first century.

The parable is Jesus’s response to two men who wanted to arrange a contract with God.

A wealthy young man approached Jesus with a question about the details of a business deal to get eternal life.

Peter and the other disciples asked another question that assumed a contract relationship with God for the service they rendered.

We often ask questions that imply we’re in a contract negotiation with God.

Jesus rejected the basic premise of those questions, which is that God enters into a contract with us.

Jesus responded to Peter’s question with grace.

He could easily have made Peter feel guilty for bringing up the question of payment.

Jesus assured Peter that he and those like him would be fully paid for their service.

Then Jesus made the statement “But many who are first will be last, and many who are last will be first” (19:30). (This principle must be pivotal in our thinking. It tells us a basic lesson about how God deals with us.)

3. We will be rewarded not on the basis of our merit but on the basis of God’s goodness and generosity. (Look at what this story shows us.) (paragraphs 24–35)

Service in the vineyard itself is a gift from God.

The workers standing idle in the marketplace just before sundown were not the idle rich. They were the idle poor.

Jesus comes to the idle, the unemployed, the lost and offers us meaningful work to do in his vineyard.

There is great fulfillment in serving the Lord in his vineyard.

Contract service—legalism—loses track of the fulfillment of having productive work to do.

(A second thing this story tells us is:)

God’s goodness always determines his rewards.

The workers received unequal treatment, but it was never unjust treatment.

God, in rewarding us, always does so out of his great generosity.

Justice forms the background against which God’s goodness appears as goodness and not unfairness.

When God deals with us, he doesn’t want to give us wages; he wants to give us rewards.

(There is something else that comes clear to us in this story:)

We have no reason to want to strike a bargain in our dealings with God.

4. Only a self-absorbed person grumbles against God’s goodness. (paragraphs 36–41)

(How do you react to God’s generosity and goodness?)

All of us appreciate God’s goodness to us and respond with appreciation to it in our lives.

The question that tests me, however, is “How do I react to the goodness of God when it is shown to others?”

All the workers were completely satisfied as long as they dealt with the vineyard owner alone.

5. Conclusion: Just as a father is honored by a son who works but doesn’t work out a “contract,” God is honored when we serve and leave the reward to him. (paragraphs 42–43)

What Shape Does This Sermon Take?

It is an inductive-deductive sermon. The idea doesn’t get stated until paragraph 22, which is well into the sermon. Once the idea is stated, it is briefly explained in paragraphs 23 and 24. Everything after that relates back to the idea and is deductive (as it always is when the idea is stated).

What Types of Supporting Material Are Used in the Sermon?

There is a great deal of restatement throughout the sermon. It appears, for example, at the close of paragraphs 9, 10, 23, and 40 in the form of questions that form transitions from section to section. There is restatement that states again the idea of the previous section at the close of paragraph 30. All of paragraph 10 is basically restatement. That is true for paragraphs 17 and 37 as well.

There is also repetition throughout the sermon. (Remember that restatement states the same thing in different words, and repetition says the same thing in the same words.) There’s a great deal of repetition in paragraphs 12–18 in order to focus on the question, “What’s in it for me?”

There is explanation in the sermon as well. Paragraph 11, for instance, explains the importance of the context. Part of paragraph 24 is an explanation of “the first will be last, and the last first.” And paragraph 32 explains how all the workers in the parable were treated with justice.

There is only one quotation in the sermon. It is the quote by Meister Eckhart found in paragraph 42. I used it because it was a helpful insight, not to quote an authority. Most people would have no idea who Eckhart was.

The sermon also contains narration. The opening eight paragraphs narrate the parable with some modern touches. Dialogue is a special type of narration, and it is sprinkled throughout the message. It’s in the conversation that Jesus had with Peter in paragraphs 19 and 20. It’s in the questions and answer in paragraphs 37 and 38.

Finally, three formal illustrations support the sermon. There is a brief illustration-quote from the Tartar tribes found in paragraph 30. (That is the only one that came from my files.) The other illustrations I used are personal. There is a brief illustration of a friend who lost his job in paragraph 26, and the sermon ends with a longer anecdote about my son in the final paragraph, which I used to sum up the central idea.

What about the Introduction to the Sermon?

An effective introduction should accomplish three objectives. It gets attention, it surfaces a need, and it orients the audience to the body of the sermon. I tried to do that. (You can judge whether I was successful.)

The opening statement—“Jesus made a wise midcareer adjustment”—was designed to get attention. Most people don’t think of Jesus having a “career” or changing jobs.

I also tried to create need based on an appeal to curiosity. I tried to tell the parable so that listeners would ask, “What’s that all about? The whole thing doesn’t seem fair. Why would Jesus ever approve of an arrangement like that?” If it works, it is because the listeners are saying to themselves, “He’s got some explaining to do this morning!”

Despite the old adage that “curiosity killed the cat, and satisfaction brought it back again,” I know that simply satisfying curiosity won’t change lives. Later in the sermon, in paragraphs 13–16, I tried to bring to the surface a deeper, more personal need. Many people feel that God doesn’t treat them fairly. That’s the fundamental need this parable addresses, but I didn’t know how to get at it directly. That’s why I started with curiosity.

While I oriented people to the Scripture passage from the start, I oriented them to the body of the sermon in paragraphs 9 and 10 by raising the question, “Why did Jesus tell this story?” Because this sermon takes an inductive rather than a deductive development, I didn’t orient listeners to the central idea or even to the subject of the sermon. Instead, I oriented them to the first movement in the message.

How about the Conclusion?

A strong conclusion brings a sermon to “a burning focus” on the great idea of the sermon. The congregation should be brought back to the concept again and feel its weight and think of its implications. I attempted to do that in two ways. First, in paragraph 42 I summarized what I had been driving at throughout the sermon. I used the quote from Meister Eckhart to repeat the main idea in a fresh way. Second, in the closing illustration about my son, I tried to get listeners to feel how God regards our positive response to his goodness.

To sum up, strong sermons should be bifocal. They must focus on the idea and the development of the text. Yet they must also focus on the listener. Through bifocal preaching, those who hear come to understand and experience what the eternal God has to say to them today.

Chapter 2   What’s the Big Idea?

Exercise 2.1   Subject and Complement

1. Subject: What is the test of a good sermon?

Complement: It reveals what you are.

2. Subject: Why has the modern pulpit lost its authority?

Complement: It has ignored the Bible.

3. Subject: How do the young and the old differ in their memories and their time?

Complement: The young have few memories and lots of time, while the elderly have lots of memories and little time.

4. Subject: Where does charity start?

Complement: Where it connects with need.

5. Subject: What should dissatisfied teenagers do?

Complement: Go it on their own if they think they know everything.

6. Subject: Who does Jesus say will enter the kingdom of heaven?

Complement: Those who do the will of the Father.

7. Subject: When does Solomon tell his readers they are to think about God?

Complement: While they are still young.

8. Subject: How does Paul tell Timothy he is to relate to others as he ministers to them?

Complement: He is to treat them as he would members of his own family.

9. Subject: What does Thielicke say is essential for forgiveness to take place?

Complement: Sin must be exposed before God.

10. Subject: Who does the psalmist say is a blessed person?

Complement: The honest individual whose sin the Lord has forgiven.

Chapter 4   The Road from Text to Sermon

Exercise 4.1   How to Identify an Author’s Big Idea

Subject: Why you should eat a toad every morning.

Complement: So nothing bad will happen that day.

Exercise 4.2   Three Developmental Questions

1. Subject: Why don’t older people learn?

Complement: They feel they already know and are too concerned about other matters.

Developmental question being addressed: Is it true? (Validity)

2. Subject: How should you listen to the Word of God?

Complement: Listen carefully and obey.

Developmental question being addressed: So what? What difference does it make? (Application)

3. Subject: How can you help your golf game in the winter?

Complement: Practice before a full-length mirror.

Developmental question being addressed: Is it true? (Validity)

4. Subject: Why does Paul tell his readers to love one another?

Complement: Because love fulfills all the demands of the law.

Developmental question being addressed: So what? What difference does it make? (Application)

5. Subject: How do we learn about reality?

Complement: We learn by repeated, unconscious experience.

Developmental question being addressed: What does it mean? (Explanation)

6. Subject: What is the importance of memory in music?

Complement: Without it we would have no melody.

Developmental question being addressed: What does it mean? (Explanation)

7. Subject: How should I live because I live only once?

Complement: Do good to others now.

Developmental question being addressed: So what? What difference does it make? (Application)

8. Subject: How have play and work lost their traditional distinctions?

Complement: What was play has been made into work, and what was work is now recreation.

Developmental question being addressed: What does it mean? (Explanation)

9. Subject: What is a result of having the law?

Complement: It prompts us to sin.

Developmental question being addressed: Is that true? (Validity)

Chapter 5   The Arrow and the Target

Exercise 5.1   Moving from the Exegetical Idea to the Theological and the Homiletical Ideas

1. Genesis 15:1–21

Exegetical idea: Abram is declared righteous (in right relationship) because he trusts God to deliver on his promises.

Theological idea: When believers trust God to deliver on his promises, they’re brought into a right relationship with him.

Homiletical idea: If we’ve become friends of Jesus, let’s trust him with our lives.

2. 2 Samuel 11:1–12:31

Exegetical idea: When David abused his power by compelling Bathsheba to come to him and murdering Uriah, he was judged by God; when David properly used his power to defeat the enemies of God’s people, he was honored.

Theological idea: Believers who abuse their power to manipulate or hurt others face God’s discipline; those who use their power to advance God’s purposes will be rewarded.

Homiletical idea: Use your power to serve God and others, rather than using it to hurt others and serve yourself.

3. Psalm 124

Exegetical idea: When Israel was delivered from oppression by God’s mighty power, they praised the Lord for his marvelous help.

Theological idea: Since almighty God always helps his people when they are in need, they should praise him.

Homiletical idea: Let’s praise almighty God for the help he’s given us this year.

4. Daniel 3:1–30

Exegetical idea: When confronted with the fiery furnace for their refusal to bow to Nebuchadnezzar’s statute, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego showed their faith in God’s power and their full devotion to him, regardless of the consequences.

Theological idea: The fires of life allow believers to show their faith and full devotion to God, regardless of the outcome.

Homiletical idea: Our faith and full devotion to God stand out in the fires of life.

5. Luke 12:13–34

Exegetical idea: Because the rich fool and his unexpected death illustrate the stupidity of greed, Christians should seek God’s kingdom and give generously of their resources to those in need.

Theological idea: Believers can avoid the foolishness of greed by centering themselves on Christ’s kingdom and living lives of generosity.

Homiletical idea: Since it’s silly to store up stuff, let’s center ourselves on Christ’s kingdom and be extravagantly generous.

6. Acts 10:1–48

Exegetical idea: God gave both Cornelius and the apostle Peter specific visions so that Peter could give the good news of the gospel to all the gentiles of Cornelius’s household.

Theological idea: God moves in the lives of both the lost and the saved in order to get the saved to give the good news of the gospel to the lost.

Homiletical idea: God moves in us, through us, and beyond us, so we can bring the gospel to all kinds of people.

7. Ephesians 1:15–23

Exegetical idea: The Ephesian believers will grow into their Christian identity as they deepen their intimacy with God, grasp their eternal destiny with him, and leverage his divine energy.

Theological idea: Believers can enhance their identities in Christ by deepening their intimacy with God, grasping their eternal destiny with him, and leveraging his divine energy.

Homiletical idea: Our identity in Christ will grow stronger as we deepen our intimacy, grasp our destiny, and leverage his energy.

8. James 2:14–26

Exegetical idea: Unlike false believers, who claim faith but show no evidence of good works, true Christians demonstrate saving faith through sacrificial obedience to God and risky love toward others.

Theological idea: False believers may claim faith but are spiritually dead because they have no works; true believers exhibit spiritual life by sacrificing for God and loving other people.

Homiletical idea: A true and saving faith in Jesus always works for God and others.

Exercise 5.3   A Lot Is at Stake!

Matthew 6:1—At stake is missing out on a reward from God.

Deuteronomy 4:1—At stake is no place to live, not even an apartment!

Ephesians 4:11–16—At stake is the church’s frailty caused when these gifts are not deployed. Also at stake is believers not living a life “worthy of the calling you have received” (v. 1). The benefit for the entire church is that the body is healthy when the gifts are deployed.

Exercise 5.4   The Power of Purpose

The evaluated behavior is that Christians don’t share the gospel and don’t know how to share the gospel.

The evaluated behavior is that listeners don’t think they need to study the Bible, nor do they study it.

The evaluated behavior is that listeners don’t know the spiritual gifts or the ones they possess.

(Note: The above behaviors could be evaluated as existing in the listeners and, therefore, as needing reinforcement. If the behaviors do not exist in the audience, the purpose statements may be stated differently.)

Chapter 8   Start with a Bang and Quit All Over

Exercise 8.1   Uncovering a Need

Record some needs of the person in the hotel.

Hope for his desperate situation. Perhaps counseling for family issues. To sober up. A friend. Financial guidance and help.

What is the need Chuck Swindoll is addressing?

The need we have to know why something bad has occurred.

Exercise 8.2   Effective Introductions

Which introduction does the better job of touching a felt need?

Introduction 2.

How does introduction 2 address a felt need of today’s society?

The speaker here is dealing with the pressure put on a Christian’s sexual purity and the corresponding need to resist temptation.

Exercise 8.3   Inconclusive Conclusions

Specifically, what is missing from the story?

What happens to the mice, the cat, and the bell? Do they place the bell around the cat’s neck? It causes the reader to wonder what happens next.

Conclusion 1

Does this ending make the story complete? Yes.

Does this ending make sense to you? No, it is confusing. You don’t know what happens with the cat, the mice, or the bell.

What does the story teach you with this ending? I guess it might teach that you should plan solutions to your problems but then ignore them and get on with what seems to be important. Or perhaps it teaches that you should plan solutions to your problems but that it is easier to not follow through on them.

Conclusion 2

Does this ending make the story complete? Yes.

Does this ending make sense to you? Yes, it tells what happens to the cat, the mouse, and the bell.

What does the story teach you with this ending? If we work together and listen to the wise, we can solve our problems.

Conclusion 3

Does this ending make the story complete? Yes.

Does this ending make sense to you? Yes, it tells what happens to the cat, the mouse, and the bell.

What does the story teach you with this ending? It is one thing to be brave in words but another thing to be brave in deeds.

Exercise 8.4   Conclusions with a Burning Focus

What does the speaker specifically want the listener to do in conclusion 1? In conclusion 2?

In conclusion 1 the speaker wants the listeners to rejoice in the face of death.

In conclusion 2 no action is called for.

How is the listener to do what the speaker suggests in conclusion 1? In conclusion 2?

In conclusion 1 the speaker wants the listener to rejoice by putting their trust in the One who holds the keys to death.

In conclusion 2 the speaker didn’t ask the listener to do anything, so there are no directions.

What might you add to each conclusion that could give the listener some action to take?

As for conclusion 1, the speaker might have said, “Many of us, like that servant, hope we can outrun death. We plan; we get health checkups; we are careful. Most of that is wisdom, some of that is fear. But we don’t have to fear.” And then they could have continued their line: “Each of us has an appointment in Samarra . . .”

As for conclusion 2, the speaker might have applied their questions about the soldier’s death to the audience’s life. For example, they might have said, “I wonder about you: What do you do when you are afraid? Most of you will never be on a battlefield, but you have other fears that are real. Do you go to Scripture to find strength to face your fears? Is it your habit to seek trust and comfort from God amid your fears? We don’t have to fear. Death is not the only certainty. Rejoicing can be a certainty if we choose to put our faith in the One who holds the keys of life and death.”

Which conclusion better gives the listener something to do? You should have checked the box for conclusion 1.

Foreword

TORREY ROBINSON

When Jim Kinney at Baker Academic told me that they wanted to put out a new edition of Biblical Preaching, I was all for it. Biblical Preaching has been possibly the most influential book on preaching for nearly half a century. If a new edition could continue to keep its message fresh for another generation, I was all for it.

I am confident that if my dad were still alive he would agree. He put in substantial time and energy to update his book twice after he first wrote it in 1980. Dad believed that the changeless truth of the Bible must be communicated in a manner relevant to a changing world. Each new edition of this book has maintained the relevance of biblical preaching. I believe this fourth edition also does this well.

I was delighted to hear that Scott Wenig had agreed to edit this edition. More than forty years ago, Scott and I were classmates and students under my father’s instruction. Over time, Scott became a distinguished teacher of preaching. I greatly appreciate Scott’s labor of love.

In the early years of my ministry as a pastor, my dad made a point to call me every week. We usually talked about family, ministry, and life. But there was always one additional question: “How’s the sermon coming?” Those treasured conversations were often private tutoring sessions. Dad has now been promoted to glory, and I dearly miss those phone calls. It is my hope that you will find in these pages not just instruction on homiletics but also an extended conversation with an amazing man who loved God and who staked his eternity on the trustworthiness of God’s Word. If you pay attention, your preaching, and God’s people, will be the better for it.

Preface to the Third Edition

Lewis Chafer began the preface to his massive eight-volume set on theology with the simple words, “To be read.” In this preface I would like to give credit to people and forces that have shaped my approach to biblical preaching, and I would appreciate if you would read it.

I have been fascinated with preaching since I was in my early teens. As a boy I began a series of diaries that recorded the tedious events of a fairly humdrum life. Years later, when cleaning out my father’s apartment, I came across one of those diaries. Apparently, on a Thursday evening I had gone to a service at the First Baptist Church in New York City to hear Dr. Harry Ironside preach. Ironside was the pastor of the Moody Church in Chicago. I can’t imagine what attracted me to a religious gathering on a Thursday evening. At the time I was sure that God kept office hours on Sunday morning. Yet I wrote in my diary, “Some preachers preach for an hour and it seems like thirty minutes; others preach for thirty minutes and it seems like an hour. I wonder what the difference is?”

I have spent my life trying to answer that question.

In college I spent many Friday evenings at the library reading books on preaching. I read several of the Yale lectures. I was swimming in deep waters, and though I didn’t fully understand what I was reading, I read anyhow. When I arrived at Dallas Seminary after graduation, I was disappointed to find there wasn’t much instruction offered on preaching. Dallas wasn’t alone in slighting the practical disciplines. Most seminaries at the time did not have courses in Christian education, counseling, pedagogy, or preaching. It was assumed, I guess, that if you knew the content you could communicate it. During my senior year, a few of my classmates asked me to teach a course in preaching on Tuesday evenings, and I agreed. I taught them all that I knew (and much I didn’t know, for that matter), and in the process I learned more about the subject of homiletics than any of the other students in the group.

After graduation I served at First Baptist Church in Medford, Oregon, and while I was there the administration at Dallas invited me to come back and help in the expanded preaching department. When I went back to my alma mater, I tried to figure out what I didn’t know about the field of communication (an enormous amount) and preaching (not a subject that academics care much about). So while I taught at the seminary, I earned a master’s degree from Southern Methodist University and after that a PhD at the University of Illinois. I minored in sociology at SMU and in radio/TV at Illinois. It turned out that I have used my minors more than my majors. All this education was an attempt to answer the question, “What makes a preacher interesting and a sermon effective?”

While at the University of Illinois I began to work through the basic elements in the preparation of sermons. The subject was not addressed directly at the university, but my first basic insight came during a class on oral interpretation. We were studying a poem by e. e. cummings that I had been assigned to deliver to the class the following week. During my preparation, I realized that we were asking the same kinds of questions to interpret the poem that we used at seminary to interpret a passage in the Bible.

During my first semester after I returned to Dallas, I read Design for Preaching by H. Grady Davis. That book changed my concept of what a sermon should be. In later years, when I was writing the first edition of Biblical Preaching, I went back to Davis’s book to give him proper credit for his ideas, and I wondered whether he would have been complimented or insulted by my references to him. I owe him a great debt, though, for the way his book influenced me.

This is the third edition of Biblical Preaching. Why a third edition? Over the years I have received a great deal of feedback from teachers and readers of the book. Most of the response has been positive, and I thank God for the way he has used Biblical Preaching in the education of those who proclaim his Word. The negative responses centered on the exercises provided to reinforce the teaching in the book. For many readers, they simply didn’t work. Robert Permenter, a graduate of the DMin program at Gordon-Conwell and a teacher of preaching at Bethel Seminary, came to my aid. Bob contributed a number of new exercises for this edition, and the two of us have tested them with students in several classes at two different seminaries. I hope you will find them helpful in understanding the counsel offered throughout this book.

Many people have contributed to my life, and if I were to try thanking all of them here by name, this preface would resemble the Manhattan telephone directory. Some friends whom I mentioned in the two previous editions have since gone on to heaven. Still, there remain several people who have made significant contributions to me and to this book over the years whom I wish to acknowledge.

Duane Litfin has been a longtime friend and colleague, and even with the enormous burden of leading Wheaton College, he took time off to teach with me in the DMin program at Gordon-Conwell.

Don Sunukjian must also be mentioned for his contribution to me and to the discipline of homiletics.

Sid Buzzell is one of the most gifted teachers I have ever known, and although he and I taught together, I believe I learned more from him about teaching than our students did about preaching.

Scott Gibson is a longtime friend and colleague who teaches the basic courses in preaching at Gordon-Conwell and does so with diligence and skill. He and his wife, Rhonda, have the gift of hospitality that has benefited both the students and me.

Nancy Hardin worked on the first edition and guarded my time so I could write.

Alice Mathews occupies a special place in my life. She contributed her skills and her time to the second edition. She is a brilliant and dedicated servant of Christ who has left her thumbprint on me and all those who have met her.

Finally, Bonnie, my wife, has been one of God’s greatest gifts to me. I’m thankful for all she has done to make my life possible. She is truly a remarkable woman.

Haddon W. Robinson

2
What’s the Big Idea?

New Concepts

Idea

Two essential elements in the statement of an idea:

Subject

Complement

I do not appreciate opera; what is worse, I have several friends who do. Being around them makes me feel as if I exist in a cultural desert, so I have taken several steps to change my condition. On occasion I have actually attended an opera. Like a sinner shamed into attending church, I have made my way to the music hall to let culture have its way with me. On most of these visits, however, I have returned home unresponsive to what the artists have tried to do.

I understand enough about opera, of course, to know that a story is being acted out with the actors singing rather than speaking their parts. Usually, though, the storyline stays as vague to me as the Italian lyrics, but opera buffs tell me that the plot is incidental to the performance. Should someone bother to ask my evaluation of the opera, I would comment on the well-constructed sets, the brilliant costumes, or the impressive range of the soprano. I could render no reliable judgment on the interpretation of the music or even the dramatic impact of the performance. When I return from the music hall with a crumpled program and an assortment of random impressions, I actually do not know how to evaluate what has taken place.

When people attend church, they may respond to the preacher like a novice at the opera. They have never been told what a sermon is supposed to do. Commonly, many listeners react to the emotional highs. They enjoy the human-interest stories, jot down a catchy sentence or two, and judge the sermon a success if the preacher quits on time. Important matters, such as the subject of the sermon, may escape them completely. Consider this anecdote told about former US president Calvin Coolidge. It’s been said that he returned home from church one Sunday and was asked by his wife what the minister had talked about. Coolidge replied, “Sin.” When his wife pressed him about what the preacher had said about sin, Coolidge responded, “I think he was against it.”

The truth is that many people in the pew would not score much higher than Coolidge if quizzed about the content of last Sunday’s sermon. To them, preachers preach about sin, salvation, prayer, or suffering all together or one at a time in thirty-five minutes. Judging from the uncomprehending way in which listeners talk about a sermon, it is hard to believe that they have listened to a message. Instead, the responses indicate that they leave with a basketful of fragments but no adequate sense of the whole.

Unfortunately, some of us preach as we have listened. Preachers, like their audiences, may conceive of sermons as a collection of points that have little relationship to one another. Three or four ideas not related to a more inclusive idea do not make a message; they make three or four sermonettes preached in succession. Reuel L. Howe listened to hundreds of taped sermons and held discussions with laypeople. He concluded that the people in the pew “complain almost unanimously that sermons often contain too many ideas.”1 That may not be an accurate observation. Sermons seldom fail because they have too many ideas; more often they fail because they deal with too many unrelated ideas.

Fragmentation poses a particular danger for the expository preacher. Some expository sermons offer little more than scattered comments based on words and phrases from a passage, making no attempt to show how the various thoughts fit together as a whole. At the outset the preacher may catch the congregation’s mind with some observation about life or, worse, jump into the text with no thought at all about the present. As the sermon goes on, the preacher comments on the words and phrases in the passage with subthemes and major themes and individual words all given equal emphasis. The conclusion, if there is one, usually substitutes a vague exhortation for relevant application, because no single truth has emerged to apply. When the congregation goes back into the world, it has received no message by which to live because it has not occurred to the preacher to preach one.

A major affirmation of our definition of expository preaching, therefore, maintains that such preaching is the communication of a biblical concept. That affirms the obvious. A sermon should be a bullet, not buckshot. Ideally, each sermon is the explanation, interpretation, or application of a single dominant idea supported by other ideas, all drawn from one passage or several passages of Scripture.

The Importance of a Single Idea

Students of public speaking and preaching have argued for centuries that effective communication demands a single theme. Rhetoricians hold to this so strongly that virtually every textbook devotes some space to a treatment of the principle. Terminology may vary—central idea, proposition, theme, thesis statement, main thought—but the concept is the same: “A speech, to be maximally effective, ought to attempt to develop more or less fully only one major proposition.”2 This thought is so axiomatic to speech communication that some authors, such as Lester Thonssen and A. Craig Baird, take it for granted: “Little need be said here about the emergence of the central theme. It is assumed that the speech possesses a clearly defined and easily determined thesis or purpose: that this thesis is unencumbered by collateral theses which interfere with the clear perception of the principal one; and that the development is of such a character as to provide for the easy and unmistakable emergence of the thesis through the unfolding of the contents of the speech.”3

Homileticians join their voices to insist that a sermon, like any good speech, embodies a single, all-encompassing concept. Donald G. Miller, in a chapter devoted to the heart of biblical preaching, insists:

Any single sermon should have just one major idea. The points or subdivisions should be parts of this one grand thought. Just as bites of any particular food are all parts of the whole, cut into sizes that are both palatable and digestible, so the points of a sermon should be smaller sections of the one theme, broken into tinier fragments so that the mind may grasp them and the life assimilate them. . . . We are now ready to state in simplest terms the burden of this chapter. It is this: Every sermon should have a theme, and that theme should be the theme of the portion of Scripture on which it is based.4

From a different tradition, Alan M. Stibbs adds a seconding voice: “The preacher must develop his expository treatment of the text in relation to a single dominant theme.”5 H. Grady Davis supports the thesis that “a well-prepared sermon is the embodiment, the development, the full statement of a significant thought.”6 A classic statement of this concept comes from J. H. Jowett in his Yale lectures on preaching:

I have a conviction that no sermon is ready for preaching, not ready for writing out, until we can express its theme in a short, pregnant sentence as clear as a crystal. I find the getting of that sentence is the hardest, the most exacting, and the most fruitful labour in my study. To compel oneself to fashion that sentence, to dismiss every word that is vague, ragged, ambiguous, to think oneself through to a form of words which defines the theme with scrupulous exactness—this is surely one of the most vital and essential factors in the making of a sermon: and I do not think any sermon ought to be preached or even written, until that sentence has emerged, clear and lucid as a cloudless moon.7

To ignore the principle that a central, unifying idea must be at the heart of an effective sermon is to push aside what experts in both communication theory and preaching have to tell us.8

Moreover, experts in social-scientific research have demonstrated time and again that people retain only one idea after listening to a sermon, a talk, or a lecture.9 It may not be what the speaker intended or hoped they would remember, but that reality proves the power of communicating a singular concept. Marketing experts know this well. They spend hundreds of hours and thousands of dollars creating thirty-second commercials that communicate just one thing (i.e., “Buy our product”). Since they’re so successful, it behooves us as preachers to take note.

No less an authority on preaching than Rick Warren highlights the necessity of focusing on one idea.

As a pastor I hate to admit this, but people don’t remember sermons or speeches—they don’t even remember paragraphs. What people remember are simple statements, slogans, and phrases. I don’t remember any speech John F. Kennedy gave, but I do remember his statements, “Ask not what your country can do for you, ask what you can do for your country” and “I am a Berliner!” Neither do I remember any sermon preached by Dr. Martin Luther King Jr., but I do remember his famous phrase, “I have a dream!”10

A novice may dismiss the importance of a central idea as the ploy of homiletics professors or prominent pastors determined to press young preachers into their mold. It should be noted, therefore, that this basic fact of communication also claims sturdy biblical support. In the Old Testament, the sermons of the prophets are called “the burden of the Lord.” These proclamations were not a few “appropriate remarks” delivered because the prophet was expected to say something. Instead, the prophet addressed his countrymen because he had something to say. He preached a message, complete and entire, to persuade his hearers to return to God. As a result, the sermons of the prophets possessed both form and purpose. Each embodied a single theme directed toward a particular audience in order to elicit a specific response.

In the New Testament, the historian Luke presents samples of the preaching that enabled the church to penetrate the ancient world. The sermons of the apostles were, without exception, the proclamation of a single idea directed toward a particular audience. Donald R. Sunukjian concludes, “Each of Paul’s messages is centered around one simple idea or thought. Each address crystallizes into a single sentence which expresses the sum and substance of the whole discourse. Everything in the sermons . . . leads up to, develops, or follows from a single unifying theme.”11

This assessment of Paul’s preaching could apply to every sermon in Acts. Each idea receives different treatment by the apostolic preacher. In Acts 2, on the one hand, on the day of Pentecost, Peter stood before an antagonistic audience and, to gain a hearing, preached an inductive sermon. His idea is not stated until the conclusion: “Let all the house of Israel know for certain that God has made Him both Lord and Christ—this Jesus whom you crucified” (Acts 2:36 NASB). In Acts 13, on the other hand, Paul used a deductive arrangement. His major idea stands at the beginning of the sermon, and the movements that follow amplify and support it. The statement found in verse 23 declares, “God, according to the promise, has brought to Israel a Savior, Jesus.”

In Acts 20, when the apostle addressed the Ephesian elders, his structure was both inductive and deductive. First, Paul drew from his own life an example of care for the church; then he warned in verse 28, “Be on guard for yourselves and for all the flock” (NASB). Having stated that central thought, Paul went on to explain it and apply it to the leaders seated before him. Not all the sermons in Acts develop in the same way, but each develops a central unifying concept.

If we preach effectively, we must know what we are about. Effective sermons major in biblical ideas brought together into an overarching unity. Having thought God’s thoughts after him, the expositor communicates and applies those thoughts to the hearers. In dependence on the Holy Spirit, the preacher aims to confront, convict, convert, and comfort men and women through the proclamation of biblical concepts. People shape their lives and settle their eternal destinies in response to ideas.

The Definition of an Idea

What do we mean when we say the word idea? A glance at the dictionary demonstrates that defining the term resembles trying to package fog. A complete definition could send us into the fields of philosophy, linguistics, and grammar. Merriam-Webster ranges all the way from “a transcendent entity that is a real pattern of which existing things are imperfect representations” to “an entity (as a thought, concept, sensation, or image) actually or potentially present to consciousness.”12

The word idea derives from the Greek word idein, which means “to see” and therefore “to know.” An idea sometimes enables us to see what was previously unclear. In common life, when an explanation provides new insight, we exclaim, “Oh, I see what you mean!” Still, another synonym for idea is concept, which comes from the verb to conceive. Just as a sperm and an egg join to produce new life in the womb, an idea begins in the mind when things ordinarily separated come together to form a unity that either did not exist before or was not recognized previously.

The ability to abstract and synthesize—that is, to think in ideas—develops with maturity. Small children think in particulars. A child praying at breakfast thanks God for the milk, cereal, orange juice, eggs, bread, butter, and jelly, but an adult combines all these separate items into the single word food. An idea, therefore, may be considered a distillation of life. It abstracts out of the particulars of life what they have in common and relates them to one another. Through ideas we make sense out of the parts of our experience.

Not all ideas, of course, are equally valid; we have good ideas and bad ideas. Bad ideas offer explanations of experience that do not reflect reality. They read into life what is not there. Often, we embrace invalid ideas because they have not been clearly stated and therefore cannot be evaluated. In our culture, influenced as it is by mass media, we are bombarded by ridiculous concepts that are deliberately left vague so we will act without thinking.

Decades ago, Marlboro cigarettes were marketed as cigarettes for sophisticated women, but Marlboro captured less than 1 percent of the market. Consumer research revealed, however, that men smoke because they believe it makes them more masculine, while women smoke because they think it makes them attractive to men. As a result of these findings, the advertisers switched their campaign away from women to men and gave Marlboros a masculine image. Rugged, weather-beaten cowpunchers were portrayed smoking cigarettes as they rounded up cattle, and the theme line invited the consumer to “come to Marlboro country.”

Because the association of cigarettes with cowboys conveyed the idea that smoking Marlboros makes men masculine, sales jumped 400 percent. The idea, of course, is nonsense. Medical evidence tells us that Marlboro country is a cemetery, and that the Marlboro man probably suffers from cancer or lung disease. (The model who originally portrayed the Marlboro man did, in fact, die of a smoking-related disease.) Yet because the idea that “smoking makes you masculine” slipped into the mind without being clearly stated, it gained wide acceptance and boosted sales dramatically.

This is not an isolated incident. When it comes to advertising, individuals are often influenced by subliminal messaging that appeals to our subconscious desires rather than to our rational thought processes. If that stands as the primary driver for what we buy, we should not be surprised that truth in advertising is hard to come by.

Ideas sometimes lurk in the attic of our minds like ghosts. At times we struggle to give these wispy ideas a body. “I know what I mean,” we say, “but I just can’t put it into words.” Despite the difficulty of clothing thought with words, we have to do it. Unless ideas are expressed in words, we cannot understand, evaluate, or communicate them. If we will not—or cannot—organize our thoughts so that we say what we mean, we have no business in the pulpit. We are like a singer who can’t sing, an actor who can’t act, or an accountant who can’t add.

The Formation of an Idea

To define an idea with “scrupulous exactness,” we must know how ideas are formed. When reduced to its basic structure, an idea consists of only two essential elements: a subject and a complement. Both are necessary. When we talk about the subject of an idea, we mean the complete, definite answer to the question, “What am I talking about?” The subject as it is used in homiletics is not the same thing as a subject in grammar. A grammatical subject is often a single word. The subject of a sermon idea can never be only one word. It calls for the full, precise answer to the question, “What am I talking about?” Single words such as discipleship, witnessing, worship, grief, or love may masquerade as subjects, but they are too vague to be viable.

A subject cannot stand alone. By itself it is incomplete, and therefore it needs a complement. The complement “completes” the subject by answering the question, “What am I saying about what I am talking about?” A subject without a complement dangles as an open-ended question. Complements without subjects resemble automobile parts not attached to a car. An idea emerges only when the complement is joined to a definite subject.

Moreover, behind every subject is a question either stated or implied. If I say that my subject is “the importance of faith,” the implied question is “What is the importance of faith?” “The people that God justifies . . .” forms a subject because it answers the question, “What am I talking about?” But the unstated question is “Who are the people God justifies?” If the words subject and complement confuse you, then try thinking of the subject as a question and your complement as the answer to that question. The two together make up the idea.

An example of a subject is the test of a person’s character. (In the form of a question, What is the test of a person’s character?) That question must be completed to have meaning. We do not by default know what the test of character is. A variety of complements could be added to this subject to form an idea. Here are a few:

The test of a person’s character is what it takes to stop them from doing something.

The test of a person’s character is what that person would do if they were certain no one would ever find out about a particular decision or action.

The test of a person’s character is like the test of an oak—How strong is the person at the roots?

Each new complement tells us what is being said about the subject, and each new complement forms a different idea.

Students of preaching must search for ideas when they read sermons or prepare sermons of their own. Davis stresses that a beginner especially must give attention to the way ideas are formed:

He must stop getting lost in the details and study the essential structure of sermons. For the time being he has to forget about the sentences, the arguments used, the quotations, the human-interest stories. He has to stand off from the sermon far enough to see its shape as a whole. Stubbornly he has to ask, “What is the man really talking about, and what are the basic things he is saying about it?” This means that he must learn to distinguish between the organic structure of the idea, on the one hand, and its development on the other. It is like beginning with the skeleton in the study of anatomy.13

Finding the subject and complement does not start when we begin construction of our sermons. We pursue the subject and complement when we study the biblical text. Because each paragraph, section, or subsection of Scripture contains an idea, we do not understand a passage until we can state its subject and complement exactly. While other questions emerge in the struggle to understand the meaning of a biblical writer, these two (“What precisely is the author talking about?” and “What is the author saying about what he is talking about?”) are fundamental.

Examples of Forming an Idea

In some biblical passages, the subject and complement may be discovered with relative ease, but in others, determining the idea stands as a major challenge. Psalm 117 is an example of an uncomplicated thought. The psalmist urges:

Praise the Lord, all nations!

Extol him, all you people!

For his love is strong;

his faithfulness eternal.

We do not understand the psalm until we can state its subject. What is the psalmist talking about? We might be tempted to say that the subject is praise, but praise is broad and imprecise. The psalmist isn’t telling us everything about praise. Nor is the subject praise of God, which is still too broad. The subject needs more limits. The precise subject is why everyone should praise the Lord. What, then, is the psalmist saying about that? He has two complements to his subject. The Lord should be praised, first, because his love is strong and, second, because his faithfulness is eternal. In this short psalm, the psalmist states his naked idea, stripped of any development, but in its bare bones, it has a definite subject and two complements.

Longer passages in which the idea receives extensive development can be harder to analyze, but the work must be done. In Hebrews 10:19–25, the author applies a previous discussion of the high-priestly work of Jesus:

Therefore, brothers and sisters, since we have confidence to enter the Most Holy Place by the blood of Jesus, by a new and living way opened for us through the curtain, that is, his body, and since we have a great priest over the house of God, let us draw near to God with a sincere heart and with the full assurance that faith brings, having our hearts sprinkled to cleanse us from a guilty conscience and having our bodies washed with pure water. Let us hold unswervingly to the hope we profess, for he who promised is faithful. And let us consider how we may spur one another on toward love and good deeds, not giving up meeting together, as some are in the habit of doing, but encouraging one another—and all the more as you see the Day approaching. (NIV)

While many details in this passage demand explanation, a careful student will distinguish the trunk from the branches. Until a subject emerges, it is not possible to determine the value or significance of anything else that is said. A casual reader might be tempted to state the subject as the high priesthood of Jesus, but that subject covers too much. The author of Hebrews does not tell his readers everything about Christ’s high-priestly work in this single paragraph. Nor is the text talking about boldness to enter the holy place, which is actually a sub-idea in the passage.

The subject can always be stated as a question. Therefore, the subject can be narrowed to “What should happen because believers can enter into God’s presence with confidence and have a great high priest?” The complements of this subject will be a series of results, and there are three. First, they should draw near to God with the assurance that comes from a cleansed heart and life; second, they should hold unswervingly to the hope they profess; and third, they should spur on one another to love and good works. Everything else in this paragraph enlarges on this subject with its complements.

Look at how the process works with the poetry in an Old Testament book. The small diary of Habakkuk consists of a series of conversations that the prophet has with God. In the opening chapter, Habakkuk is upset with God for not punishing evil in the nation of Judah and in the broader world. We must first state the ideas behind the prophet’s grievances.

Habakkuk opens with a complaint in 1:2–4. Stated as a subject and complement, this is the idea:

Subject: What is Habakkuk’s lament about the injustice he sees in Judah?

Complement: He wonders why God, who is righteous, doesn’t judge the nation for its sin.

Idea: Habakkuk laments that his righteous God does not punish sin in Judah.

God replies to the prophet in verses 5–11. God’s answer can also be stated as a subject and complement:

Subject: How will God bring judgment on Judah?

Complement: He will use the wicked Babylonians to punish his people.

Idea: God will use the wicked Babylonians to punish his people.

Note that both of these paragraphs (vv. 2–11) can now be joined in a larger subject and complement:

Subject: How will God punish the evil and injustice rampant among his people, Judah?

Complement: God will use the wicked Babylonians as his whipping stick.

Idea: God will judge the evil among his own people, Judah, through an invasion by the wicked Babylonians.

That leads us, then, to the third paragraph of the passage, found in 1:12–2:1:

Subject: How could a righteous God use the evil and godless Babylon to punish a more righteous nation like Judah?

Complement: God will also punish the Babylonians at an appointed time.

Idea: Even though God will use the wicked Babylonians to punish Judah, he will also judge the Babylonians for their sin.

There are many images used in the poetry of this chapter, but they must be separated from the ideas they support. It is important to go through the process of stating the subject and complement to get at the ideas. Ideas are slippery creatures that can easily escape your grasp.

To take one more example, this time from narrative literature, we turn to the book of Genesis and its story of the patriarch Abraham. The subject of Abraham’s life as recounted in Genesis 12–23 is “What does a life lived by faith in God look like?” In chapter 13 Abram and his family have returned to the Promised Land from Egypt, only to face a major conflict over the limited resources of the land. In faith and in contradiction to cultural norms, Abram allows his nephew Lot to choose whatever portion of the land he desires. Lot sees the Jordan Valley and goes there despite its contamination by the wickedness of Sodom and Gomorrah. God then comes to Abram and affirms his faithful action by reiterating his promises of both the land and innumerable descendants. In obedience Abram moves through the land as God commands, and he worships him at Hebron. Thus, the subject, complement, and idea are as follows:

Subject: How did Abram reveal his genuine faith in God in his conflict with Lot over the land’s limited resources?

Complement: He resolved the conflict by showing open-handed generosity, trusting God to provide for him in the face of apparent loss.

Idea: To resolve his conflict with Lot over the limited resources of the land, Abram showed open-handed generosity, revealing his genuine faith in God to provide in the face of his apparent loss.

In each of these passages, we determined the subject and its complement(s) to discover the structure of the idea. In order to think clearly, we must constantly distinguish the idea from the way the idea develops. The effort to state the idea of a passage and then to state the idea of our sermon in exact words can be frustrating and irritating, but in the long run, it is the most economical use of our time. What is more important, we cannot get anywhere without doing it. We do not understand what we are reading unless we can clearly express the subject and complement of the section we’re studying. And those who hear us preach do not understand what we’re saying unless they can answer the basic questions: What were we talking about today? What were we saying about what we were talking about? Yet Sunday after Sunday, men and women leave church unable to state the preacher’s basic idea because the preacher has not bothered to state it in the sermon. When people leave church in a mental fog, they do so at their spiritual peril.

Thinking is difficult, but it stands as our essential work. Make no mistake about the difficulty of the task. It is often slow, discouraging, overwhelming. But when God calls us to preach, he calls us to love him with our minds. God deserves that kind of love, and so do the people to whom we minister.

On a cold, gloomy morning, a preacher worked on his sermon from breakfast until noon with little to show for his labor. Impatiently, he shut down his laptop and looked disconsolately out the window, feeling sorry for himself because his sermons came so slowly. Then there flashed into his mind an insight that had profound effect on his later ministry. “Your fellow Christians,” he thought, “will spend far more time on this sermon than you will. They come from a hundred homes. They travel hundreds of miles in the aggregate to be in the service. They will spend three hundred hours participating in the worship and listening to what you have to say. Don’t complain about the hours you are spending in preparation and the agony you experience. The people deserve all you can give them.” Challenged and inspired, he opened his laptop and got back to work on his message.

DEFINITIONS

Complement—the answer to the question, “What exactly am I saying about what I’m talking about?”

Idea—a distillation of life that abstracts out of the particulars of experience what they have in common and relates them to one another.

Subject—the complete, definite answer to the question, “What am I talking about?”

Questions and activities for this chapter can be found in the student exercises section at the back of the book.

1 Howe, Partners in Preaching, 26.

2 Litfin, Public Speaking, 80. See also the discussions of the central idea in Schultze, Essential Guide to Public Speaking, 57–59; Dickens, Speech, 58, 254–56, 267–71; and Gallo, Talk like TED, 183–201.

3 Thonssen and Baird, Speech Criticism, 393.

4 D. Miller, Way to Biblical Preaching, 53, 55 (emphasis original).

5 Stibbs, Expounding God’s Word, 40.

6 H. Davis, Design for Preaching, 20.

7 Jowett, Preacher, 133.

8 See further Stanley and Jones, Communicating for a Change, 101–16; Carter, Duvall, and Hays, Preaching God’s Word, 101–3; and Hulst, Little Handbook for Preachers, 71–72.

9 Gallo, Talk like TED, 183–88.

10 Warren, Purpose Driven Church, 101.

11 Sunukjian, “Patterns for Preaching,” 176.

12 Merriam-Webster.com, s.v. “idea,” accessed June 6, 2024, https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/idea.

13 H. Davis, Design for Preaching, 27.

© 1980, 2001, 2014, 2025 by Haddon W. Robinson

Published by Baker Academic

a division of Baker Publishing Group

Grand Rapids, Michigan

BakerAcademic.com

Ebook edition created 2024

All rights reserved. No part of this publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any form or by any means—for example, electronic, photocopy, recording—without the prior written permission of the publisher. The only exception is brief quotations in printed reviews.

Library of Congress Cataloging-in-Publication Data is on file at the Library of Congress, Washington, DC.

ISBN 9781540967916 (cloth) | ISBN 9781493449521 (ebook) | ISBN 9781493449538 (pdf)

Unless otherwise indicated, Scripture quotations are the author’s translation.

Scripture quotations labeled ASV are from the American Standard Version of the Bible.

Scripture quotations labeled KJV are from the King James Version of the Bible.

Scripture quotations labeled NASB are from the (NASB®) New American Standard Bible®, Copyright © 1960, 1971, 1977, 1995, 2020 by The Lockman Foundation. Used by permission. All rights reserved. www.lockman.org

Scripture quotations labeled NIV are from the Holy Bible, New International Version®. NIV®. Copyright © 1973, 1978, 1984, 2011 by Biblica, Inc.™ Used by permission of Zondervan. All rights reserved worldwide. www.zondervan.com. The “NIV” and “New International Version” are trademarks registered in the United States Patent and Trademark Office by Biblica, Inc.™

Scripture quotations labeled NKJV are from the New King James Version®. Copyright © 1982 by Thomas Nelson. Used by permission. All rights reserved.

Scripture quotations labeled RSV are from the Revised Standard Version of the Bible, copyright 1946, 1952 [2nd edition, 1971] National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America. Used by permission. All rights reserved worldwide.

Cover design by Paula Gibson

Baker Publishing Group publications use paper produced from sustainable forestry practices and postconsumer waste whenever possible.

Student Exercises

Here are some exercises you can do to help nail down the concepts we have discussed. Some are more difficult than others. All of them have been tested in real-life situations with people like you. I have included exercises from previous editions of this book that I developed in the courses I have taught. I have dusted them off and gotten rid of any “cobwebs,” so that you have clear exercises to work with. Several of the activities come from Dr. Robert Permenter, a former student of mine at Gordon-Conwell Theological Seminary. Bob is a pastor who has taught preaching courses at Bethel Seminary, and I appreciate his contribution here. Other exercises come from Scott Wenig, editor of the fourth edition, who also holds the Haddon Robinson Chair of Biblical Preaching at Denver Seminary.

Working through these exercises can be both interesting and frustrating. After all, thinking can be hard work. Completing them, however, should help you better grasp and apply the material presented in Biblical Preaching.

Chapter 7   Making Dry Bones Live

This chapter teaches you the accurate use of supporting material in relation to an idea, and it helps you use supporting material appropriately.

To accomplish this, be familiar with the words and concepts in chapter 7 of the text. Also, understand that the term type refers to the types of supporting material discussed in chapter 7, whereas material is used interchangeably with supporting material.

Supporting material exists in a sermon to make an abstract idea specific and vivid. It makes abstract ideas understandable, believable, and easier to apply. Big ideas and outlines are typically abstract. Abstractions in and of themselves are rarely convincing, memorable, or even applicable. People make important decisions and set goals based on abstract ideas (e.g., on principles), but abstract ideas need supporting material to accomplish their purposes. Without that support noble and good ideas may be forgotten or simply ignored.

Exercise 7.1   Move That Stone!

Read the following quote, then answer the question. Don’t overthink it; spend about a minute or less on your answer.

If you look up Sisyphus in your dictionary, you will discover that he was a mythological figure in Homer’s Odyssey, a Greek poem written more than a millennium before Christ. His punishment was to perform a meaningless task.

What image comes to mind as a result of reading the above paragraph?

Now read the following quote and record the image that comes to your mind. Again, don’t overthink it.

If you look up Sisyphus in your dictionary, you will discover he was a mythological figure in Homer’s Odyssey, a Greek poem written almost a millennium before Christ. Poor Sisyphus. Homer portrays him in hell, and this was his punishment: “And I saw Sisyphus in violent torment, seeking to raise a monstrous stone with both his hands. Verily he would brace himself with hands and feet, and thrust the stone toward the crest of a hill, but as often as he was about to heave it over the top, the weight would turn it back, and then down again to the plain would come rolling the ruthless stone. But he would strain again and thrust it back, and the sweat flowed down from his limbs, and dust rose up from his head.”1 Poor Sisyphus, doomed to an eternity of rolling that huge stone up the hill, only to have it roll back down; only to struggle with it back up the hill, only to have it roll back down; over and over throughout eternity. Long hours, difficult labor, in a pointless and meaningless task.

What image comes to mind as a result of reading the above paragraph?

(Check the answers in “Answers to Student Exercises” at the back of the book.)

The difference between the two paragraphs is supporting material. Both paragraphs give the same idea; however, the second paragraph has supporting material. The second paragraph leaves a stronger impression on you than the first, which is reflected by the image you recorded. Supporting material is important because it leaves a strong impression of an abstract idea with the listener.

REVIEW

Supporting material is important because it makes a strong impression of an abstract idea on the listener.

Supporting material is used accurately when the main idea of the supporting material is similar to the idea it represents.

Supporting material is used appropriately when the intent of the supporting material is similar to the intent of the idea it supports.

Five uses of supporting material are to amplify, to explain, to prove, to apply, and to make appealing.

Chapter 8   Start with a Bang and Quit All Over

Exercise 8.1   Uncovering a Need

When preparing an introduction, raise a felt need in your audience. A need is anything lacking in a person. By definition, a felt need is a need that a person currently feels. Not every need is a felt need. Read the story below and answer the question that follows.

A man calls his pastor on Monday morning in desperation. “Pastor, you have to help me,” he says. “Friday morning I was fired, and when I came home, my wife said she was leaving me for another man. My kids hate me; I got drunk on the weekend, was evicted, and stayed at this cockroach hotel. My CPA said I am financially bankrupt. Pastor, I really need your help.”

Record some needs of the person in the hotel.

It isn’t hard to imagine the kind of help this guy might ask from his pastor. The story actually ends with him asking for help. After the guy unloads all his troubles, he says, “Pastor, I really need your help. The one thing I need to know is . . . the beast in Revelation 16—is that literal or not? Please, Pastor, can you tell me?”

Whether you think this story is sad or funny, it is unlikely you recorded that he needed to understand the significance of the beast in Revelation 16. Does the man in the hotel have a need to know about the beast in Revelation? Sure. Does he have a felt need to know about it? Probably not at this time. Therefore, a question that helps develop a good introduction is this: What does the audience feel is lacking in life? Naturally, the question needs to be related to the sermon’s big idea. Felt needs can be:

financial

emotional (grief, depression, need for encouragement)

physical (fatigue from a busy schedule)

moral (“How do I behave . . . ?”)

intellectual

relational

spiritual

ego-related

leadership-related

communicatory

career-related

This list is by no means exhaustive. It is a launching point to stir your thinking. Your audience can be lacking something in any of these areas. When the people in an audience understand you not only care about their needs but are trying to address them from the Bible, their attention will be natural, and the message will be more effective.

Read the following introduction by Chuck Swindoll that appeared in the section “An Effective Introduction Uncovers Needs” in chapter 8. Then record the need Swindoll is addressing.

El Tablazo looked so close. Too close. It happened so fast. Exploding into the jagged 14,000-foot peak, the DC-4 disintegrated with a metallic scream.

What was left of the Avianca Airline flight bound for Quito, Ecuador, flamed crazily down the mountainside into a deep ravine. One awful moment illuminated a cold Colombian mountain in the night, then the darkness returned. And the silence.

Before leaving the airport earlier that day, a young New Yorker named Glenn Chambers hurriedly scribbled a note on a piece of paper he found on the floor of the terminal. The scrap was part of a printed advertisement with a single word, “Why?” sprawled across the center.

Needing stationery in a hurry, Chambers scrawled a note to his mother around the word in the middle. Quickly folding this last-minute thought, he stuffed it in an envelope and dropped it in a box. There would be more to come, of course. More about the budding of a lifelong dream to begin a ministry with the Voice of the Andes in Ecuador.

But there was no more to come. Between the mailing and the delivery of Chambers’ note, El Tablazo snagged his flight and his dreams from the night sky. The envelope arrived later than the news of his death. When his mother received it, the question burned up at her from the page—Why?

It is the question that hits first and lingers longest. Why? Why me? Why not? Why this?

What need is Chuck Swindoll addressing?

(Check your answer in “Answers to Student Exercises” at the back of the book. While it is not crucial that your answer match exactly, it is important to understand the process of addressing a felt need in preparing introductions, and your answer should be in the ballpark.)

Exercise 8.2   Effective Introductions

Below are two introductions that present the same topic. Read them and answer the questions that follow.

Introduction 1 (a pastor talking to his congregation)

John and I have been friends for a long time. He served on the trustee board, had a beautiful wife, two children, and a career that made most men envious. His wife called me one day and said John had left her for another woman and asked if I would talk to him. I did and tried to convince him that his decision was wrong, but it was no use. He wouldn’t listen. I told him adultery was wrong and he shouldn’t engage in it. I told him the sexual desires for this other woman would decrease, that it was hurting his kids, and that God said in the seventh commandment not to commit adultery.

Introduction 2

In his book The Myth of the Greener Grass, J. Allan Petersen tells the story of a woman who was at lunch with eleven other people. They had been studying French together while their children were in a nursery school. This woman asked the group, “How many of you have been faithful to your husbands throughout your marriage?” Only one woman at the table raised her hand.

That evening the woman who asked the question told her husband the story and added that she herself had not raised her hand. “But I have been faithful,” she assured him.

“Then why didn’t you raise your hand?” he asked.

“I was ashamed.”

Ashamed of fidelity! In the past the burden of shame fell on those who broke their vows, but in our society, that has changed. Only killjoys still believe in fidelity. Most sex in movies is not between married people. The impression given is that those who live in the fast lane are the only ones who know what life is all about. Everyone else is out of step with society. One recent survey suggests that perhaps as many as one half of all marriage partners, at some time or another, have an affair. Yet the seventh commandment says . . .

Which introduction does the better job of touching a felt need?

Both introductions introduce the topic, but the second one does a better job of introducing a felt need of the audience. How does introduction 2 address a felt need of today’s society?

Exercise 8.3   Inconclusive Conclusions

Read the story below and answer the questions that follow.

An old cat was in the habit of catching all the mice in the barn. One day the mice met to talk about the great harm that it was doing to them. Each one told of some plan by which to keep out of its way. “Do as I say,” said an old gray mouse that was thought to be very wise. “Do as I say. Hang a bell around the cat’s neck. Then, when we hear it ring, we shall know that it is coming and can scamper out of its way.” “Good! Good!” said all the other mice, and one ran to get the bell.

THE END

Even though it claims “The End,” the story is not complete. Specifically, what is missing?

Following are several possible conclusions. Read each conclusion and answer the questions that go along with it before moving on to the next one.

Conclusion 1

The old gray mouse asked, “Who will hang the bell on the cat?” One mouse said, “I need to work on my house.” Another mouse said, “I must work on being a good parent.” The old gray mouse then started a school to help mice be better social creatures.

Is the story complete?   YES or NO

Does this ending make sense to you? What does the story teach with this conclusion?

Conclusion 2

The old gray mouse asked, “Who will hang the bell on the cat?” One mouse said, “Let’s draw straws.” But the old gray mouse said, “Do it together. That is the only way you can succeed.” They found the cat sleeping, and together they hung the bell around its neck. Together they saved themselves from harm.

Is this story complete?   YES or NO

Does this ending make sense to you? What does the story teach with this conclusion?

Conclusion 3

“Now, which of you will hang the bell on the cat’s neck?” said the old gray mouse. “Not I! Not I!” said all the mice together. And they scampered away to their holes.

Is this story complete?   YES or NO

Does this ending make sense to you? What does the story teach with this conclusion?

The original story demonstrates that an incomplete conclusion is a confusing conclusion (because it doesn’t conclude). The first possible conclusion demonstrates that the conclusion must relate to your big idea to avoid confusion. The last two conclusions teach that the conclusion has to be stated clearly or else the audience may be led down a path the speaker doesn’t intend.

To identify clear conclusions, then, you must realize that an incomplete conclusion or a conclusion not related to the big idea confuses the audience.

Exercise 8.4   Conclusions with a Burning Focus

Read the following two sermon conclusions, the first of which is also found in the section “The Conclusion” in chapter 8. Refrain from looking at the questions until after you have finished reading both conclusions.

Conclusion 1

An old legend tells of a merchant in Bagdad who one day sent his servant to the market. Before very long the servant came back, white and trembling, and in great agitation said to his master: “Down in the market place I was jostled by a woman in the crowd, and when I turned around I saw it was Death that jostled me. She looked at me and made a threatening gesture. Master, please lend me your horse, for I must hasten away to avoid her. I will ride to Samarra and there I will hide, and Death will not find me.”

The merchant lent him his horse and the servant galloped away in great haste. Later the merchant went down to the market place and saw Death standing in the crowd. He went over to her and asked, “Why did you frighten my servant this morning? Why did you make a threatening gesture?”

“That was not a threatening gesture,” Death said. “It was only a start of surprise. I was astonished to see him in Bagdad, for I have an appointment with him tonight in Samarra.”

Each of us has an appointment in Samarra. But that is cause for rejoicing—not for fear, provided we have put our trust in Him who alone holds the keys of life and death.

Conclusion 2

The Civil War was a time that tested our nation’s character and tested the character of men. Any war is a time of test and a time of fear, for death can ring at our front door unexpectedly.

After the battle of Richmond, the body of a Union soldier was found. He had sacrificed himself in the battle on the altar of truth. He was discovered in an unusual way: his hand was resting on a book. His finger lay positioned on these words: “Yea, though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil, for thou art with me.”

I wonder about that soldier. Was he wounded while reading the text? Was he shot and then knowing that he might not make it, struggle to his pack of supplies till he found his Bible? Did he choose this text, or did it just open there from the natural wear and tear of him reading the Bible? Was it his habit to find comfort from God in times of need? The soldier died, but he apparently did so without fear.

What does the speaker specifically want the listener to do in conclusion 1? In conclusion 2?

1 ____________

2 ____________

Check your answers before continuing. Try to grasp the reasoning behind the answer, then continue to the next question and do the same. Repeat this process until you have answered all the questions.

How is the listener to do what the speaker suggests in conclusion 1? In conclusion 2?

1 ____________

2 ____________

What might you add to each conclusion that could give the listener some action to take?

1 ____________

2 ____________

Based on the above questions and thought, check the conclusion that better gives the listener something to do.

▢ Conclusion 1

▢ Conclusion 2

One way a speaker can produce a burning focus is to state specifically what they want the audience to do and then how to do it. Conclusion 1 does that better than conclusion 2. The difference turns on three phrases in conclusion 1:

“Each of us has an appointment in Samarra” (You should be aware that you will die someday.)

“that is cause for rejoicing [for you]” (But you make death a cause of rejoicing rather than fear.)

“provided we have put our trust in Him” (This is how we can rejoice.)

The speaker wants the listener to do these three things. Conclusion 2, while clear, never asks the listener to do anything. Still, both conclusions can ask for more-specific action, as demonstrated in the answers section.

Chapter 9   The Dress of Thought

Exercise 9.1   Choosing Words for Clarity

This activity helps you choose clear words for your sermon. Read the following example, looking for words and phrases that are not clear. It may be confusing, but read both paragraphs in their entirety.

To aspire to quantify the activity of the Midwestern Region amidst the proscription of God to David for such endeavors (2 Sam. 24:2ff) creates tension which resolves itself in the postulate that stewards prove themselves accountable with equating either the pace of activity or the results of the activity with success. Each item, because of His presence within that entity, has intrinsic ultimate value apart from linking those items into an annual evaluation. But I do enumerate the past year as part of this report, and I offer to elucidate, upon request, any issue.

If the student work provides a “paean of mien” the graduate rubric, with notable exceptions, might read, “atrophy amidst entropy.” While a Regional Director considers SCP to fulcral a graduate lifestyle understandably ascribes SCP importance locally to a secondary or tertiary role personally for involvement and envisages success in what the Regional Director “produces,” not to mention (but here I do!) the Central Office. The vestigial archetype of SCP as members determining the Society which they comprise (and not the stuff) while assisted by the staff (Field and Central) will be resurrected (or memorialized) as national economic and spiritual attrition enervates the scope and abilities of the staff.2

List words, word phrases, or abbreviations with which you are unfamiliar. Feel free to stop when you have listed ten of them!

Why are the words not clear?

The words are not clear because they are unfamiliar. If you said the words are unclear because they are new, unusual, unknown, and so on, you are basically on target.

Exercise 9.2   You Say Tomato; I Say Tomato Paste

Words have to be specific as well as familiar to be clear. Since abstract words are always vague, the preacher should identify abstract words and substitute them with more-specific words. Abstract words are the result of omitting details. Specific words form as details are added to a sermon. The more abstract your word or concept, the fewer details surrounding your word; the fewer details surrounding your word, the more likely an audience is to give it an unintended meaning or fall asleep. The lack of clarity results in confused listeners.

The following is a list of abstract phrases and more-specific corresponding phrases. Read the list and note the details of the specific phrases that are absent in the corresponding abstract phrases.

Abstract Words | Specific Words
Many foreign cars | 61% of Toyotas
In the near future | Two weeks from now
A few good men | American generals in Iraq War
A tragedy | Thousands died
Fast airplane | Twin-engine jet
A good book | The Bible
A few flowers | A dozen roses
A tree | A pine tree

In the following activity, write specific words to the corresponding abstract words. (Note: answers will vary.)

Abstract | Specific
Building | _____________________
Tool | _____________________
Road | _____________________
Garment | _____________________
Holiday | _____________________
Vehicle | _____________________

Exercise 9.3   As Bad as It Gets

Short sentences and simple grammatical structure also produce clarity. The purpose of a manuscript is to expose awkward thoughts in your mind. The following activity uncovers another characteristic for clear writing.

Read the first sentence in the first quoted paragraph in exercise 9.1 above. How many words are in that sentence? ____________ Make sure you have the right answer or an approximately close answer to that question. It is obvious that a sentence with that many words does not follow the general rule of clear writing. No one talks like that on purpose, and when you write a manuscript, you lessen the possibility of talking like that in a sermon.

Although this isn’t a grammar lesson, we need to consider grammar to write clearly. The following questions pertain to the same sentence you just read from exercise 9.1. Take your time, and give your best answers.

What is the main verb in this sentence? ____________

What is the main subject in this sentence? _____________________

What is the independent clause in this sentence? _____________________

(Check your answers in “Answers to Student Exercises” at the back of the book.)

Exercise 9.4   Concrete Words

This activity helps you identify and use vivid words. To complete this activity, keep the following definitions clear from chapter 9 of the text. Specific words are abstract words with details. Concrete words are specific words with a picture.

Following is the same list of abstract and more-specific phrases from exercise 9.2. Here they are also made concrete. Read the list from left to right, starting with the abstract column. Note how the idea moves from abstract to specific to concrete.

Abstract Words | Specific Words | Concrete Phrases
Many foreign cars | 61% of Toyotas | One out of every five cars you pass on the road
In the near future | Two weeks from now | During the Super Bowl
A few good men | American generals in Iraq War | Colin Powell, Norman Schwarzkopf, Tommy Franks
A tragedy | Thousands died | The 2011 Japan earthquake
Fast airplane | Twin-engine jet | The Concorde
A good book | The Bible | The book of Psalms
A few flowers | A dozen roses | Roses in my neighbor’s garden
A tree | A pine tree | The Christmas tree in my living room

As you move from left to right, you become more attentive. The same happens with an audience. When you move from abstract words to concrete words, an audience’s attention becomes more focused.

In the following activity, write concrete words to corresponding specific words. Use the specific words provided in the answer section or copy the specific words you used in exercise 9.2.

Abstract | Specific | Concrete
Building | ____________ | ____________
Tool | ____________ | ____________
Road | ____________ | ____________
Garment | ____________ | ____________
Holiday | ____________ | ____________
Vehicle | ____________ | ____________

A concrete expression may be difficult for an audience to visualize if it has no personal experience of the concrete word. In such a case, it may be better to use a specific word.

1 Homer, The Odyssey ¶593.

2 Litfin, Public Speaking, 279.

Preface to the Fourth Edition

Preaching has stood at the center of the church since the day of Pentecost. Few people understood this better than Haddon Robinson. His magnum opus, Biblical Preaching, catalyzed a renaissance in homiletics when it was first published in 1980. With its focus on the methodology of big idea preaching, it revitalized the study and practice of expository preaching nationally and, over time, even globally. Haddon formulated his approach to preaching while teaching at Dallas Seminary but brought it to fruition as president of Denver Seminary from 1979 to 1991. From the moment Biblical Preaching came out, it was devoured by professors, pastors, and homiletically minded lay people alike. And as its sales figures over the decades show, it remains the go-to text on how to create and preach expository sermons rooted in a singular idea.

Anyone familiar with the art and craft of homiletics knows that various other preaching books, many of great value, have been published over the past forty-plus years. While some of these take issue with big idea methodology, all of them are indebted to Haddon’s unceasing focus on talking to people about themselves from the Bible. In a day when innumerable voices on the internet, television, and social media scream for our attention, preaching the Scriptures in a clear and relevant manner has never been in greater demand. Into this cacophony, Haddon’s voice continues to come through loud and clear.

This fourth edition of Biblical Preaching is essentially the same as the book’s earlier iterations. It still unpacks all the essential steps in creating a big idea expository sermon from the exegesis of the biblical text to its delivery to hungry people so in need of spiritual help and guidance. Those familiar with this methodology will notice that I have added an additional step called the theological idea when moving from the exegetical idea to the creation of the homiletical or preaching idea. Haddon’s intuitive brilliance allowed him to make a seamless connection between the exegetical idea and the homiletical idea. But as I’ve taught his approach over the past thirty years, I’ve come to realize that the intermediate step of formulating the theological idea is of great value in helping students with this part of the process. The remaining revisions are mainly concerned with the changing cultural landscape that we now inhabit as well as providing some updated resources for further study. Lord willing, this new edition of Biblical Preaching will help maintain its central role in helping men and women communicate God’s Word. Its clarity, style, and use of illustrations, as well as its proven methodology, make it a must-have for all pastors and would-be preachers.

I first met Haddon when I was a student at Denver Seminary, and he quickly became a mentor, model, and spiritual influence on me. Haddon knew God, knew his Word, and those realities were reflected both in his casual conversations and when he stood at the pulpit. In time, Haddon blessed me with an invitation to serve as an adjunct professor in homiletics, and as God’s grace allowed, I eventually came to serve as the Haddon Robinson Chair of Biblical Preaching at Denver Seminary. I can never thank Haddon enough for teaching me how to preach and for the privilege of following in his footsteps. Moreover, his children, Torrey and Vicki, have blessed me more than I can say by inviting me to revise their father’s book for another generation of preachers. May God use it for his glory and the expansion of his church.

Scott Wenig
Haddon Robinson Chair of Preaching
Denver Seminary

Bibliography

Adams, Jay. Preaching with Purpose. Grand Rapids: Zondervan, 1986.

Allen, Ronald J., and Gilbert L. Bartholomew. Preaching Verse by Verse. Louisville: Westminster John Knox, 1999.

Alter, Robert. The Art of Biblical Narrative. Rev. ed. New York: Basic Books, 2011.

———. The Art of Biblical Poetry. Rev. ed. New York: Basic Books, 2011.

Anderson, Lynn. If I Really Believe, Why Do I Have These Doubts? Rev. ed. New York: Simon and Schuster, 2000.

Bacon, Francis. “Of Studies.” In The Major Works, edited by Brian Vickers. Oxford World’s Classics. Oxford, UK: Oxford University Press, 1996.

Baillie, D. M. To Whom Shall We Go? 1955. Reprint, Grand Rapids: Baker, 1974.

Bambaeeroo, Fatemeh, and Nasrin Shokrpour. “The Impact of the Teachers’ Non-verbal Communication on Success in Teaching.” Journal of Advances in Medical Education and Professionalism 5, no. 2 (2017): 51–59.

Barclay, William. A Spiritual Autobiography. 1960. Reprint, Louisville: Westminster John Knox, 2001.

Barnhouse, Donald Grey. Let Me Illustrate: More than 400 Stories, Anecdotes, and Illustrations. 1967. Reprint, Grand Rapids: Revell, 1994.

Baumann, J. Daniel. An Introduction to Contemporary Preaching. Grand Rapids: Baker, 1972.

Beecher, Henry Ward. Yale Lectures on Preaching. New York: J. B. Ford, 1872.

Booth, John Nicholls. The Quest for Preaching Power. New York: Macmillan, 1943.

Bright, John. The Authority of the Old Testament. 1967. Reprint, Grand Rapids: Baker, 1975.

Brooks, Phillips. Lectures on Preaching. New York: Dutton, 1877.

Brown, Charles R. The Art of Preaching. New York: Macmillan, 1922.

Bryant, Donald C., and Karl R. Wallace. Fundamentals of Public Speaking. 3rd ed. New York: Appleton-Century-Crofts, 1960.

Buttry, Daniel L. First-Person Preaching: Bringing New Life to Biblical Stories. Valley Forge, PA: Judson, 1998.

Campbell, Ernest T. Locked in a Room with Open Doors. Waco: Word, 1974.

Carson, D. A. New Testament Commentary Survey. 7th ed. Grand Rapids: Baker Academic, 2013.

Carter, Terry G., J. Scott Duvall, and J. Daniel Hays. Preaching God’s Word: A Hands-On Approach to Preparing, Developing, and Delivering the Sermon. 2nd ed. Grand Rapids: Zondervan, 2018.

Chapell, Bryan. Christ-Centered Preaching: Redeeming the Expository Sermon. 3rd ed. Grand Rapids: Baker Academic, 2018.

Chappell, Clovis G. Questions Jesus Asked. 1948. Reprint, Grand Rapids: Baker, 1974.

Cohen, Arthur R. “Need for Cognition and Order of Communication as Determinants of Opinion Change.” In The Order of Presentation in Persuasion, edited by Carl I. Hovland, 79–97. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1966.

Craddock, Fred B. As One without Authority. 4th ed. Nashville: Christian Board of Publication, 2001.

———. Preaching. 25th anniv. ed. Nashville: Abingdon, 2010.

Davies, Gwilym. Get Preaching: Application. Fearn, UK: Christian Focus, 2020.

Davis, Flora. “How to Read Body Language.” In The Rhetoric of Nonverbal Communication: Readings, edited by Haig A. Bosmajian, 3–14. Glenview, IL: Scott, Foresman, 1971.

Davis, H. Grady. Design for Preaching. Philadelphia: Muhlenberg, 1958.

Dickens, Milton. Speech: Dynamic Communication. New York: Harcourt, Brace, 1954.

Doriani, Daniel M. Putting the Truth to Work: The Theory and Practice of Biblical Application. Phillipsburg, NJ: P&R, 2001.

Duduit, Michael, ed. Handbook of Contemporary Preaching: A Wealth of Counsel for Creative and Effective Proclamation. 2nd ed. Nashville: B&H Academic, 2024.

Duffy, Martha, and Richard Schickel. “Kubrick’s Grandest Gamble.” Time, December 15, 1975.

Earls, Aaron. “Americans’ Trust of Pastors Hovers Near All-Time Low.” Lifeway Research. January 22, 2021. https://research.lifeway.com/2021/01/22/americans-trust-of-pastors-hovers-near-all-time-low.

Edwards, J. Kent. Effective First-Person Biblical Preaching: The Steps from Text to Narrative Sermon. Grand Rapids: Zondervan, 2009.

Eisenson, Jon, and Paul H. Boase. Basic Speech. 3rd ed. New York: Macmillan, 1975.

Ekman, Paul. “Facial Expressions of Emotion: New Findings, New Questions.” Psychological Science 3, no. 1 (1992): 34–38.

Everding, H. Edward, Jr., and Dana W. Wilbanks. Decision Making and the Bible. Valley Forge, PA: Judson, 1975.

Fadiman, Clifton, ed. The Little, Brown Book of Anecdotes. Boston: Little, Brown, 1985.

Fee, Gordon D., and Douglas Stuart. How to Read the Bible for All Its Worth. 4th ed. Grand Rapids: Zondervan, 2014.

Flesch, Rudolf. The Art of Plain Talk. New York: Harper, 1946.

Forsyth, P. T. Positive Preaching and the Modern Mind. Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 1964.

Freeman, Harold. Variety in Biblical Preaching. Waco: Word, 1987.

Freud, Sigmund. Collected Papers. Vol. 3. New York: Basic Books, 1959.

Friesen, Garry. Decision Making and the Will of God. With J. Robin Maxson. Rev. ed. Sisters, OR: Multnomah, 2004.

Gallo, Carmine. Talk like TED: The Nine Public-Speaking Secrets of the World’s Top Minds. New York: St. Martin’s, 2014.

Garner, Stephen Chapin. Getting into Character: The Art of First-Person Narrative Preaching. Grand Rapids: Brazos, 2008.

Gauss, Christian. The Papers of Christian Gauss. Edited by Katherine Gauss Jackson and Hiram Haydn. New York: Random House, 1957.

Glynn, John. Commentary and Reference Survey: A Comprehensive Guide to Biblical and Theological Resources. 10th ed. Grand Rapids: Kregel Academic and Professional, 2007.

Goldsworthy, Graeme. Preaching the Whole Bible as Christian Scripture. Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 2000.

Grasham, John A., and Glenn G. Gooder. Improving Your Speech. New York: Harcourt, Brace, 1960.

Gray, Giles W., and Claude M. Wise. The Bases of Speech. 3rd ed. New York: Harper, 1959.

Green, Michael P., ed. Illustrations for Biblical Preaching. Grand Rapids: Baker, 1989.

Gregory, Joel C. “It’s Good to Get Out Alive.” Preaching Today. Accessed March 26, 2024. https://www.preachingtoday.com/sermons/sermons/2013/may/its-good-to-get-out-alive.html.

Greidanus, Sidney. Preaching Christ from the Old Testament: A Contemporary Hermeneutical Method. Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 1999.

Hall, Edward T. The Silent Language. 1959. Reprint, Greenwich, CT: Fawcett, 1968.

Hals, Ronald M. The Theology of the Book of Ruth. Philadelphia: Fortress, 1969.

Hamilton, J. Wallace. Who Goes There? What and Where Is God? Westwood, NJ: Revell, 1958.

Haselden, Kyle. The Urgency of Preaching. New York: Harper and Row, 1963.

Hayakawa, S. I. Language in Thought and Action. 2nd ed. New York: Harcourt, Brace, and World, 1964.

Hercus, John. David. 2nd ed. Chicago: InterVarsity, 1968.

Hoekema, Anthony A. The Four Major Cults. 1963. Reprint, Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 1989.

Homer. The Odyssey. In Complete Works of Homer: The Iliad, The Odyssey, The Homeric Hymns. Translated by Andrew Lang. Kyiv, Ukraine: Strelbytskyy Multimedia Publishing, 2021.

Howe, Reuel L. Partners in Preaching: Clergy and Laity in Dialogue. New York: Seabury, 1967.

Hubbard, Robert L., Jr. The Book of Ruth. New International Commentary on the Old Testament. Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 1988.

Hughes, R. Kent. 1001 Great Stories and Quotes. Wheaton: Tyndale, 1998.

Hulst, Mary S. A Little Handbook for Preachers: Ten Practical Ways to a Better Sermon by Sunday. Downers Grove, IL: InterVarsity, 2016.

Hunt, George. “Editor’s Note: Attila the Hun in a Tattered Sweater.” Life, November 13, 1964.

Jowett, J. H. The Preacher: His Life and Work. 1912. Reprint, Grand Rapids: Baker, 1968.

Kaiser, Walter C., Jr. Toward an Exegetical Theology: Biblical Exegesis for Preaching and Teaching. Grand Rapids: Baker, 1998.

Keller, Tim. Preaching: Communicating Faith in an Age of Skepticism. New York: Viking, 2015.

Kidner, Derek. Proverbs. Downers Grove, IL: IVP Academic, 2008.

Kim, Matthew D., and Scott M. Gibson, eds. The Big Idea Companion for Preaching and Teaching: A Guide from Genesis to Revelation. Grand Rapids: Baker Academic, 2021.

Koller, Charles W. Expository Preaching without Notes. Grand Rapids: Baker, 1962.

Lewis, C. S. Mere Christianity. New York: Macmillan, 1952.

Lewis, Ralph L., with Gregg Lewis. Inductive Preaching: Helping People Listen. Wheaton: Crossway, 1983.

Litfin, Duane. Public Speaking. 2nd ed. Grand Rapids: Baker, 1992.

Longman, Tremper, III. Old Testament Commentary Survey. 5th ed. Grand Rapids: Baker Academic, 2013.

Lowry, Eugene L. Doing Time in the Pulpit: The Relationship between Narrative and Preaching. Nashville: Abingdon, 1985.

———. The Homiletical Plot: The Sermon as Narrative Art Form. Exp. ed. Louisville: Westminster John Knox, 2000.

Maclaren, Alexander. Expositions of Holy Scripture. 1912. Reprint, Grand Rapids: Baker, 1988.

Macpherson, Ian. The Art of Illustrating Sermons. 1964. Reprint, Grand Rapids: Baker, 1976.

Mager, Robert F. Preparing Instructional Objectives. 2nd ed. Belmont, CA: Fearon, 1975.

Marshall, Peter. John Doe, Disciple: Sermons for the Young in Spirit. Edited by Catherine Marshall. New York: McGraw-Hill, 1963.

Maslow, Abraham H. Motivation and Personality. 3rd ed. London: Longman, 1987.

Mathewson, Steven D. The Art of Preaching Old Testament Narrative. 2nd ed. Grand Rapids: Baker Academic, 2021.

Meyer, F. B. Expository Preaching: Plans and Methods. 1910. Reprint, Ireland: CrossReach, 2022.

Miller, Alexander. The Renewal of Man: A Twentieth-Century Essay on Justification by Faith. Garden City, NY: Doubleday, 1955.

Miller, Donald G. The Way to Biblical Preaching. New York: Abingdon, 1957.

Minnick, Wayne C. The Art of Persuasion. Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1957.

Monroe, Alan H. Principles and Types of Speech. 3rd ed. Chicago: Scott, Foresman, 1949.

Monroe, Alan H., and Douglas Ehninger. Principles and Types of Speech Communication. 7th ed. Glenview, IL: Scott, Foresman, 1974.

Ortberg, John. The Life You’ve Always Wanted: Spiritual Disciplines for Ordinary People. 1997. Reprint, Grand Rapids: Zondervan, 2015.

Overdorf, Daniel. Applying the Sermon: How to Balance Biblical Integrity and Cultural Relevance. Grand Rapids: Kregel Academic and Professional, 2009.

Paget, Richard. Human Speech: Some Observations, Experiments, and Conclusions as to the Nature, Origin, Purpose, and Possible Improvement of Human Speech. New York: Harcourt, Brace, 1930.

Palmer, Earl F. Love Has Its Reasons: An Inquiry into New Testament Love. Waco: Word, 1977.

Pelsma, John R. Essentials of Speech. Rev. ed. New York: Crowell, 1924.

Plantinga, Cornelius, Jr. Reading for Preaching: The Preacher in Conversation with Storytellers, Biographers, Poets, and Journalists. Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 2013.

Quayle, William A. The Pastor Preacher. 1910. Reprint, Manila, Philippines: Lifeline Philippines, 1984.

Reid, Loren D. Speaking Well. Columbia, MO: Artcraft, 1962.

Reu, J. M. Homiletics: A Manual of the Theory and Practice of Preaching. Translated by Albert Steinhaeuser. 1924. Reprint, Grand Rapids: Baker, 1967.

Robinson, Haddon W. Biblical Sermons. Grand Rapids: Baker, 1989.

———. “The Heresy of Application.” Leadership, Fall 1997.

Robinson, Haddon W., and Torrey W. Robinson. It’s All in How You Tell It: Preaching First-Person Expository Messages. Grand Rapids: Baker Books, 2003.

Rowell, Edward K. Fresh Illustrations for Preaching and Teaching. Grand Rapids: Baker, 1997.

Ruskin, John. Sesame and Lilies: Two Lectures. Edited by Robert Kilburn Root. New York: Henry Holt, 1904.

Ryken, Leland, and Tremper Longman III, eds. A Complete Literary Guide to the Bible. Grand Rapids: Zondervan, 1993.

Sangster, William E. The Craft of Sermon Construction. 1951. Reprint, Grand Rapids: Baker, 1972.

Schaeffer, Francis A. True Spirituality. Wheaton: Tyndale, 1971.

Schopenhauer, Arthur. The Art of Literature. Translated by T. Bailey Saunders. 6th ed. 1910. Reprint, Mineola, NY: Dover, 2004.

Schultze, Quentin J. An Essential Guide to Public Speaking: Serving Your Audience with Faith, Skill, and Virtue. 2nd ed. Grand Rapids: Baker Academic, 2020.

Soper, Donald O. The Advocacy of the Gospel. New York: Abingdon, 1961.

Spurgeon, C. H. The Autobiography of Charles H. Spurgeon. Vol. 1, 1834–1854. Chicago: Curtis and Jennings, 1898.

Stanley, Andy, and Lane Jones. Communicating for a Change: Seven Keys to Irresistible Communication. Colorado Springs: Multnomah, 2006.

Steinbeck, John. Travels with Charley: In Search of America. 1966. Reprint, London: Penguin, 1980.

Stewart, James S. The Gates of New Life. 1940. Reprint, Grand Rapids: Baker, 1972.

Stibbs, Alan M. Expounding God’s Word: Some Principles and Methods. Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 1961.

Stonehouse, Ned B. “The Areopagus Address.” In Paul before the Areopagus and Other New Testament Studies, 1–40. 1957. Reprint, Eugene, OR: Wipf and Stock, 2022.

Stott, John. Between Two Worlds: The Challenge of Preaching Today. 1982. Reprint, Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 2017.

Strunk, William, Jr., and E. B. White. The Elements of Style. 4th ed. New York: Macmillan, 2000.

Sunukjian, Donald R. Invitation to Biblical Preaching: Proclaiming Truth with Clarity and Relevance. Grand Rapids: Kregel Academic and Professional, 2007.

———. “Patterns for Preaching: A Rhetorical Analysis of the Sermons of Paul in Acts 13, 17, and 20.” ThD diss., Dallas Theological Seminary, 1972.

Sweazey, George E. Preaching the Good News. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice Hall, 1976.

Swindoll, Charles R. For Those Who Hurt. 1977. Reprint, Grand Rapids: Zondervan, 1995.

———. Saying It Well: Touching Others with Your Words. New York: FaithWords, 2012.

———. The Tale of the Tardy Oxcart and 1501 Other Stories. Nashville: Word, 1998.

Thielicke, Helmut. Encounter with Spurgeon. Translated by John W. Doberstein. 1963. Reprint, Cambridge: Lutterworth, 2016.

Thompson, Wayne N. Quantitative Research in Public Address and Communication. New York: Random, 1967.

Thonssen, Lester, and A. Craig Baird. Speech Criticism: The Development of Standards for Rhetorical Appraisal. New York: Ronald, 1948.

Thoreau, Henry David. A Week on the Concord and Merrimack Rivers. 1849. Reprint: London: Heritage, 2014.

Tizard, Leslie J. Preaching: The Art of Communication. London: Allen and Unwin, 1958.

Tozer, A. W. Of God and Men: Cultivating the Divine/Human Relationship. 1960. Reprint: Chicago: Moody, 2015.

Vines, Jerry, and Jim Shaddix. Power in the Pulpit: How to Prepare and Deliver Expository Sermons. Chicago: Moody, 2017.

Wainwright, Arthur. Beyond Biblical Criticism: Encountering Jesus in Scripture. London: SPCK, 1982.

Waltke, Bruce K. “Proverbs 10:1–16: A Coherent Collection?” In Reading and Hearing the Word from Text to Sermon: Essays in Honor of John H. Stek, edited by Arie C. Leder, 161–80. Grand Rapids: Calvin Theological Seminary and CRC Publications, 1998.

Warren, Rick. The Purpose Driven Church: Growth without Compromising Your Message and Mission. Grand Rapids: Zondervan, 1995.

Wharton, Tim. Pragmatics and Non-verbal Communication. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2009.

Whitehead, Alfred North. The Aims of Education, and Other Essays. 1929. Reprint, Washington, DC: Free Press, 1967.

Whitesell, Faris D., ed. Great Expository Sermons. Westwood, NJ: Revell, 1964.

Whitesell, Faris D., and Lloyd M. Perry. Variety in Your Preaching. Old Tappan, NJ: Revell, 1954.

Whitman, Walt. Complete Prose Works. New York: D. Appleton, 1881.

Willhite, Keith, and Scott Gibson, eds. The Big Idea of Biblical Preaching: Connecting the Bible to People. 1998.

Williams, George G. Creative Writing for Advanced College Classes. Rev. ed. New York: Harper, 1954.

Zuck, Roy B. Basic Biblical Interpretation: A Practical Guide to Discovering Biblical Truth. Colorado Springs: David C. Cook, 1991.